<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great evil of health-drinking, or, A discourse wherein the original evil, and mischief of drinking of healths are discovered and detected, and the practice opposed with several remedies and antidotes against it, in order to prevent the sad consequences thereof.</title>
            <author>Morton, Charles, 1627-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41897</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1689</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23417</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12068480</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12068480</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53440</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41897)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53440)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 71:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great evil of health-drinking, or, A discourse wherein the original evil, and mischief of drinking of healths are discovered and detected, and the practice opposed with several remedies and antidotes against it, in order to prevent the sad consequences thereof.</title>
                  <author>Morton, Charles, 1627-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>xvi, 128 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonathan Robinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to C. Morton. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. xvi.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Temperance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Drinking customs --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53440:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53440:1"/>
            <p>THE GREAT EVIL OF Health-Drinking: OR A Diſcourſe, wherein the Original, Evil, and Miſchief of drinking of Healths, are diſcovered and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected; and the Practice oppoſed.</p>
            <p>With ſeveral Remedies and Antidotes againſt it, in order to prevent the ſad Conſequences thereof.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 20.1.</hi>
               </bibl> Wine is a Mocker, ſtrong Drink is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging: and whoſoever is deceived thereby, is not wiſe.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Jonathan Robinſon,</hi> at the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Lion in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, MDCLXXXIV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:53440:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:53440:2"/>
            <head>A ſerious Addreſs TO Governours and Governed.</head>
            <p>I Shall more certainly come near the Mark I aim at, by flying low in a Supplication, than high in a Dedication; of which I know more than one moſt Worthy, if the Building were not too little for a ſtately Front, and too mean to bear an Inſcription in Great Letters, and whoſe Worth might cover my Preſumption in appearing in the World. I am perfectly of the mind of a late worthy Perſon, who <hi>cared not whether it were known there was ſuch a perſon in the World, if he might but do good while he was in it.</hi> I ſtudy neither for temporal Rewards, nor Praiſe, but for the Good of thoſe I cannot ſpeak, nor write to. And that I may the eaſier obtain, what I earneſtly deſire of you, I will firſt humbly ſupplicate, what no Man can with any reaſon deny, and then what they ſhould grant.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="iv" facs="tcp:53440:3"/>
               <hi>1.</hi> I beſeech you labour to maintain and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Purity of Society, which every Man is bound to do, next to the Purtiy of his own Soul and Body. Here we make choice of them, with whom we are to live for ever. The Comfort and Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Society in this Life, as in the way to Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs in Heaven, doth conſiſt in inoffenſive, uſeful, and as much as poſſibly we can attain to, untainted, innocent, and holy Converſation. Is not Society much broken and ſtain'd by theſe Cups which are a Vehicle of Exceſs and Corruption?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> I beſeech you conſider, that Mankind hath nothing ſince the Fall, but what cometh through the Hands of Chriſt. <hi>And God made</hi> Adam <hi>and</hi> Eve <hi>Coats of Skins, and cloathed them,</hi> but it was after the Promiſe of Chriſt was made, <hi>Gen. 3.21.</hi> And what comes to us by his means, that was not purchaſed by his Blood? and what was purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by his Blood, was not intended to be abuſed and thrown away by the Receivers, or taken to their hurt.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Can it be thought that our bleſſed Lord did faſt, and ſuffer Hunger, endure Temptation, ſweat drops of Blood, complain, <hi>I thirſt?</hi> Did Water and Blood run out of his Sides, to obtain for us a wanton Liberty, to deceive our ſelves, and enſnare others? to tempt, overthrow, infatuate? to make ſport with the Gifts of his Bounty, ordained for his Glory, and our cheerful ſerving of ſo good a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter?</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="v" facs="tcp:53440:3"/>
               <hi>4.</hi> Did he who made a Plenty out of great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to a fainting Multitude, command that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be loſt, but that the very Crumbs and Frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhould be gathered, yet allow ſuch a Waſte as is made by Healthing? Or can we think, that he who taught us to pray for daily Bread, can approve of ſuch an Inſtitution as this is, an Invention to make the abuſe of Plenty the more ſpecious? Is not Healthing a very Vanity, and the Superfluity of Vanity? what is there in it to commend it to Obſervation? It is now coming up apace to be placed among Duties, and it is exacted from them that have no Inclination to it, they are call'd upon to do it, as with an <hi>Hoc age.</hi> But the nearer it approacheth towards the Altar of Duties, the more Care ſhould be to thruſt it down, or turn it out of doors, to its Profane and Pagan Company. Is it not to be admired, that ſo empty a Ceremony ſhould be coming up to be a ſtated and ſolemn Service?</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> Conſider, I pray you, if we know the uſe of Time, which is our All to prepare for an approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eternity, and the uſe of Plenty, the Benefit and Comfort of Society, what the right Enjoyment of Friends is, and what our very Bodies are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for; we would not throw away not a piece of a Day upon ſuch an Exerciſe as drinking Healths; no, not a moment in ſuch a Service. I can no better compare theſe Cups, than to Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Pots that water the Garden of Vices, which come up ſo faſt and thick.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="vi" facs="tcp:53440:4"/>
               <hi>6.</hi> Suppoſe we had a Soveraignty over our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants the Creatures, and might do what we pleaſed with them, we might uſe them, or throw them away; yet certainly we muſt give an account of our ſelves to God before his Judgment-Seat, and of our Actions, whether good or evil. <hi>Can any Man reduce Healthing, drinking under that Notion and Formality,</hi> to the order of good Actions, by which God is glorified, <hi>our ſelves and others bettered?</hi> I am ſure, we muſt in our eating and drinking, as by a Divine Law, in a poſitive way glorify God.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7.</hi> I beſeech you, conſider, are not the Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of God ſo full and big, that they are ready to break down upon us in ſore Judgments and Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations? And our Sins are as legible in the late Threatning Providence, as was the Sin of the old World, or the Sin of <hi>Sodom.</hi> Whoſe Fleſh hath not ſmarted with that greateſt, ſtrongeſt freezing, that any Man can remember? True, by the Goodneſs of God, there is plenty of Corn in the Land; but what became of our Drink, was it not quite out in many, near out in moſt good Houſes? what became of our Bread? Have we not ſeen a hoar Froſt, and Rime upon the outſide of it, and an Ice within? What became of our Wind and Water Mills? thoſe Grinders ceaſed in many places. I am not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant what may be ſaid to all this. But can any Man tell what our Corn in the Ground may come to? what our Flocks and Herds may come to? or
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:53440:4"/>what may become of theſe Bodies of ours? of the Health we yet enjoy? And that this ſhould befal us at that time, wherein our bleſſed Saviour is more forgotten than remembred, and diſhonoured by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable Riot and Exceſs, is not to be neglected. Surely drinking is grown to a height and great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, and Healthing helps it on, and is an Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that has the force of an Engine to carry it up, as a Provocation, nearer Heaven. <hi>Surely</hi> God calls <hi>to a Repentance,</hi> to a ceaſing from this Sin; and I am as ſure, that if <hi>Drinking fall,</hi> Health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will fall with it, and as long as Healthing is maintained, Drinking will keep its courſe. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon theſe Conſiderations, I do moſt humbly and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly addreſs my Supplications:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> To the Men of Honour and Power, to them that put on Scarlet by their Office, and fare deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly every day; and to them that for the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure of their Office, have the Government of great Corporations upon their Shoulders; that they would refrain from, or reſtrain the luxuriant Growth of Immorality, which is fed by the waſte of Drink. If you would drain the Chanel, ſtop this Humour of Healthing, which is one of the livelieſt Springs of it. Some of old have well ſaid, that Majeſty was begotten in Wedlock between Reverence and Honour. It is not good for Honour to be alone, when you ſit in the State of your Office. Let not Reverence be forced to quit the Room, while Healths are drunk to your Honour. Reverence takes it ill to be
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:53440:5"/>affronted by that Boldneſs. Some Countries for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad drinking Wine to Magiſtrates. But <hi>Nehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> who lived in great Honour, and kept a noble Houſe, had plentiful Supplies of all ſorts of Wine. <hi>Neh. 5.</hi> It is lawful for you to keep great Houſes, open Tables, and to drink Wines; but if you would have God to think upon you for Good, make that great Man your Example; and in this alſo a greater than he, <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> at whoſe Feaſts none did compel. <hi>Eſth. 1.8.</hi> And this being written be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore time in the Holy Scripture, is written for our Learning: And whether drinking Healths be not a moral Compulſion, tho not violent, is humbly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and alſo atteſted, by <hi>Gaſper Sanctius</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that place: <hi>Cum Principium aut Amicorum ſalus interponitur, nemo poterit non obtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare. —</hi> [<hi>A Lapide</hi> to the ſame ſenſe. <hi>Aug. Serm. de Temp.</hi> hereafter quoted.] I do not by this tax or accuſe, for I am a Stranger to the great and ſun ptuous Tables that are kept; but I do humbly beſeech them, that think it a neceſſary part of the Grandure of our Metropolis, to conſider how many Companies, and Meetings of Veſtry-men and others, they become Examples and Authorities to, and how impoſſible it is to reſtrain this Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance (this is a very diminutive Word) in the City Youth, which are ſo commonly poiſoned by theſe Draughts, as long as they have the Warrant of ſuch Examples. Theſe have been the parting Cups to many from all Modeſty and Vertue, and 'tis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:53440:5"/>known, to the great Sorrow of many Friends, where Young Men began their Journey to a far Country, where they are yet loſt, and not found. <hi>Luke 15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> I deſire Parents, [and who will hear me, if they will not, in what I deſire of them, for the ſake of God and all that is dear to them, and their Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity?] that they both by early Inſtruction, ſtrict In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, and exemplary Practice, reſtrain their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren from the Entrance into this kind of Learning. It was a wiſe Apothegm of Reverend Mr. <hi>Dod,</hi> (whom <hi>Learned</hi> Capel <hi>called</hi> John <hi>the Divine,</hi> and the worthy Dr. <hi>Harris</hi> ſaid, ſpake better Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thegms than <hi>Plutarch,</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>If Fathers would but ſtudy to be as good themſelves, as they would have their Children be, the World would be better.</hi> I know ſome that are very obſerving and wiſe, that do much complain of the danger of ſending their Sons abroad for Education, and into Callings. Drinking prepares for Debauchery; and they, like young Swimmers, dabble firſt about the Banks, but grow modiſh, and then confident, by Healths, and keep ſo long to that Element, till they grow ſtark giddy, are drown'd, or take Surfeits, and are hardly, if ever recovered. Healthing is to be abhorred for this Effect of it, that it makes young <hi>Men confident;</hi> and their ſeeing it the current Practice, Genteel, Modiſh, their being abroad a while to ſee Faſhions more than to follow Studies, gives Reputation and Encouragement to their Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence:
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:53440:6"/>And then turn or ſtop them if you can! If you would have your Sons keep from Debauchery, and running into Ruine before your Eyes, keep them from dabling.</p>
            <q>St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> the he preach'd twice before the ſame day, caus'd to be aſſembled not only Old Men, but Women and Children to his Church in <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po,</hi> that they might fear as long as they lived, becauſe of what had happened that day. <hi>Cyril,</hi> an eminent Citizen of <hi>Hippo,</hi> had an only Son, <hi>eum ſuperfiuè diligebat, &amp; ſupra Deum;</hi> he loved him ſuperfluouſly, and more than God, and they both are fallen into the Ditch. The Father being drunk with ſuperfluous Love, forbore to correct him, and indulged him to do what he pleaſed. How came they both to fall into the Ditch? but becauſe the Father was blind, and fond, and naught, and neglected his own, and Children's Salvation. And now, behold your <hi>Cyril</hi> had a Son, as you know, whom he neglected to correct, and he did luxuriouſly conſume part of his Father's Goods, and now he was overcome with Drunkenneſs, <hi>(oppreſſit nequiter)</hi> he wickedly abuſed his own Mother, forward with Child; he would have violated his Siſter; he hath kill'd his Father, and wounded his two Siſters to death.— <hi>O doloroſa Ebrietas! &amp;c.</hi> O moſt grievous Drunkenneſs! the Mother of all Evils, the Siſter of all Luxury, the Father of all Pride. O Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nneſs, thou doſt blind the Mind, haſt loſt all Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="xi" facs="tcp:53440:6"/>haſt no Wiſdom or Counſel; thou art a flattering Devil, ſweet Poiſon. O Drunkenneſs! let Men learn to know thee, to avoid thee; And again, to avoid thee, to run from thee, as from Death: for he that covets thee, ſhall not obtain the Kingdom of Heaven. It is not enough for all the Faithful to abſtain from it themſelves, but they that abſtain, to teach others to abſtain from it, &amp;c. <hi>Ad Fratr,</hi> &amp;c. <bibl>
                  <hi>ſ. 33. com. 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>May you not as well teach them the Modes of Swearing, as the Arts of Drinking? may you not as ſafely put them to nurſe to <hi>Volupia,</hi> as initiate them in the Rites of <hi>Bachus?</hi> As you would keep them chaſt, be ſure you keep them ſober; or elſe if they do not kill you, they will break your Hearts, and kill Joy and Hopes at your very Hearts.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> I earneſtly entreat Governours, Tutors and Maſters in every Faculty: If Youths had no rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal So uls, they would have no need of your Skill, and they would be of no uſe to you; you have therefore the Care of Souls; your Charge is great, and your Work difficult. Some muſt be broken from ill Cuſtoms learn'd before they came to you; and ſome muſt be preſerved from Infection, that come untainted to you. Rules of Art are not more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary than Regulation of Life<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, you know the Power of Example. If there be any ſpark of Light, if any Divine Authority in what is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to you; Let none that are under your Care have cauſe to ſay, they had your Example for this
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:53440:7"/>playing upon the ſlippery Brink of the Whirlepool of that drowning Sin of Drunkenneſs. I ſay again, Healthing gives young Men confidence to drink; and how can you take them down, if you ſet up the mode? I have more than once, with ſome ſadneſs, read the Oration of the Learned <hi>Sixtinus Arnama,</hi> when Rector of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of <hi>Frankere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See the laſt Edit. of his Antibai ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Bible.</note> where he gives a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable account of the <hi>German</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, and particularly of that; and among other things, ſaid this, <hi>Multos generoſae indolis &amp; magnae ſpei Adoleſcentes, quos Parentes &amp; Praeceptores integros vitae à ſe dimiſerant, &amp; indulgens haec mater acceperat, intra paucos dies, per initiales iſtas Potationes, quibus in ipſo introitu Bacho, id eſt, Diabolo initiabantur, corruptos vidimus, &amp; poſteà mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerè periiſſe audivimus.</hi> I do not ſay, he means Healths by thoſe <hi>Initiales Potationes,</hi> thoſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring Drinkings, by which they were baptized to <hi>Bachus,</hi> that is, the Devil. But is not the Form of Healthing now in uſe, the Form of Admiſſion into ſuch Fraternities? Allow but Liberty in this, as in a harmleſs thing, and if ever you can reſtrain them from turning round and giddy in the courſe of Sin, or cure them of that Epidemical Vice, you may be more famous than the famous Stroker, and be even a <hi>Thaumaturgus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> I humbly beſeech the Reverend and Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Clergy, who are the Standards of this Age,
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:53440:7"/>to continue, as I hope they will, in a wiſe and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Abſtinence, and, if I may uſe the Word without Offence, Nonconformity to the exorbitant Humour of Healthing, as famous Mr. <hi>Bolton</hi> call'd it, when it was nothing ſo much in faſhion as now it is. By this you preſerve the Dignity of your Calling, as much as by any thing in your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Converſation, even in the Opinion of thoſe great Men, that ſeem pleaſed for the time, with them that miniſter in theſe Offices. By this, as by other Decencies of your Calling, you maintain an Authority of being heard, when you adviſe, admoniſh; rectify without a ſilencing Repulſe of, <hi>Phyſician, heal thy ſelf;</hi> or, Pull out the Beam out of thine own Eye. It was counted no better than a Scandal in former times, and there is no reaſon why it ſhould be accounted profitable in this Age, much leſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable. The Reverend Writer of the Life of the moſt Fatherly Biſhop <hi>Lake,</hi> ſets out his noble and charitable Hoſpitality, when Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells,</hi> that his conſtant Family commonly conſiſted of at leaſt fifty Perſons: Now in this Rankneſs of Houſe-keeping, I know it is a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe that commonly falls upon great Families, that they grow diſorderly and riotous—which fault leſt any Man ſhould ſuſpect to be in his Houſe, I cannot but remember another Virtue of his, <hi>1 Tim. 3.4.</hi> For notwithſtanding his large Allowance of all things fit for the Entertainment of Strangers, you ſhould ſee no Footſteps of Riot or Exceſs
<pb n="xiv" facs="tcp:53440:8"/>in his Houſe: <hi>No tippling or carouſing of Healths,</hi> &amp;c. Vertues and Vices do not change Places and Natures, with Times and Humours. How unſuitable is it, for the ſame Hands that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter the Cup of Bleſſing, with a ſolemn Prayer for the Soul and Body of the Receiver, to hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout theſe <hi>Sacramenia,</hi> as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> calls them, with Head uncovered, Bows and Reverence, and implied Prayers, which avail not, but oftentimes do actually Harm to both Soul and Body.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> I apply my ſelf with an importunate Requeſt to them that are in the Flower of their Age, that are the Nurſery of the Church and Common-wealth, the young Gentleman, and Youth of all Profeſſions, that they would ſeriouſly look into this little <hi>Manual,</hi> as into a Glaſs, that is intended to inform, and not to decoive. You are coming into the World to act your Part; you carry with you the Hoarts and Hopes of Parents; the World will be good or bad as you prove, when your Fathers are gone before, either haſtned to their Grave with Sorrow by you, or comforting themſelves in ſeeing you tread in the right Path before they dye. <hi>Juventas</hi> was of old a Goddeſs; ſhe is now known to be what ſhe is, but ſtill the wicked One doth court her, and would fain be great with her, and if he can get her Heart, what ſhall ſhe not have? even half his Kingdom. But be not deceived, leſt you be deſtroyed, firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved, and then lost. He will cheat you till your Fyes are out, and then abuſe you, yea, make you
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:53440:8"/>grind in his Mill. You walk upon a Sea of Glaſs, and dazling Vanities and Shews, Pageants and Pleaſures, and falſe Images of things hang out to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and divert you from the ſcope of your Life, and main Buſineſs. You have need of a ſtrong Guard, a well-reſolved Heart ſeaſoned with Grace, and a ſteady Head. Satan conveys his Poiſon in Wines and pleaſing Liquors, and they are handed to you by your Friends, that are unhappily drawn in; and their Virtue is to intoxicate, and to deprive you of the excellent Faculty of diſcerning between Good and Evil, of the Capacity of doing good, (for that is loſt while the Fit is upon you) and all your Power united for doing Evil. You may ſee in a little time that there is nothing ſo childiſh and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly, nothing ſo bold and daring, whether they be in Oaths and Blaſphemies againſt God, or hazard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Life; nothing ſo obſcene and filthy, nothing ſo baſe and falſe; in a word, nothing ſo ſinful and abominable, but is done and practiſed by the giddy and debauch'd Perſon, who is inſpired with Wine, elevated into a Madneſs, and unman'd in a Puppet, acted as the infernal Spirit hangs him upon his Wyres, and blows him with the Wind of his Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. He plays foul upon you, and makes the World believe it is Health you drink for, but do not you ſee what it proves? It is Health by an <hi>Antiphraſis.</hi> You may deſire to ſee Countries and Faſhions, but of all Lands take heed of <hi>Crapulia,</hi> and of all Company avoid the Carnaliſts, and of
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:53440:9"/>all the Faſhions, the Faſhions of them that wear the Garments ſpotted with the Fleſh. If once you like to be a Carnaliſt, you may quickly become Atheiſt, Papiſt, Heathen, any thing. I do hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pray for you, and ſhall do while I live, that you may be holy and harmleſs, the Children of a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father.</p>
            <p>To Conclude, I beſeech every one that reads this little Book, would receive every Beam of Light that ſhines upon it, as from the Father of Lights, and kindly and gently breath upon every Spark of Divinity and Reaſon, to keep it in, and make it burn, to dry the unwholeſom Moiſture of evil Habits and Manners, and to warm and foment the fainting languid Spirits of Grace and Goodneſs.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 16. line 24. r. <hi>to the Sin forbidden.</hi> P. 41. l. 22 r. <hi>Amos</hi> 6.6 P. 44. l. 2. r. <hi>provocandi.</hi> P. 49. l. 21. r. <hi>Romanorum.</hi> P. 52. l. 1. r. <hi>Plautus</hi> f. <hi>Paulus.</hi> &amp; l. 26. r. <hi>a,</hi> &amp; l. 27. r. <hi>and.</hi> P. 55. l. 8. r. <hi>Annam,</hi> &amp; l. 26. r. <hi>Perenna.</hi> P. 68. § 2. r. <hi>Drink, or Ordeal</hi> f. <hi>Order,</hi> which in the <hi>Saxon</hi> ſignifies Judgment, of which Sir <hi>Hen. Spelman's.</hi> Gloſs at large. P. 92. l. 10. r. <hi>as oft as any of them will drink to him again.</hi> P. 96. l. 16. r. <hi>even</hi> f. <hi>ever.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53440:9"/>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>THE Introduction.</head>
               <p>IF Health-drinking can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be of a bad Original, as it is found to be of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Tendency, it can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver become a wholeſom Practice, though it could be reduced to its prime Original; if we could cut off the Cuſtom from its old Root of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſm and Barbarity, and graft it upon better Reaſons. We plainly ſee in daily and dear experience, the Fruit to be deadly to very many, and good for none; many are the worſe, and none the better for it. Were it a Phyſical Potion for Health, none would drink it, but ſuch as value Health: but as very a Vanity as it is, being diſſolved in a pleaſing Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53440:10"/>it is commended, and it is taken by Quarts and Pottles, by them that love the Liquor, better than the Health of Body and Soul. Health is the Inſcription and Title upon the Glaſs; but they that taſte it, find themſelves no better by it; and they that largely drink, are conſtantly the worſe. What tho? Can I think that Men will leave it, or thank me for their Information? Can it be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, that Men will do by this, as by other things, if they be good for nothing, and if they do more hurt than good, throw them away? Or rather, is it not to be feared, that they who are as dry and open as a Spunge, to ſwallow down the Modes of Sin and Vanity, will be tenacious, and as hard as a Flint to retain them? As long as I ſee the Sacred Oracles disbelived, the Holy Commandments diſobeyed, known Sins committed, and known Duties negleced, and Things contrary to the Law of Grace and Nature commonly practiſed; no Man can expect, much leſs can I, that what is offered to the World with the beſt Affection and Intention, ſhall be kindly entertained of all, or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53440:10"/>received by them that ſtand in moſt need of Inſtruction and Correction. Phyſicians write of Diſeaſes and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, not expecting that every Man that is diſeaſed will apply the Remedies, and wax better by them. Here are ſome Antidotes for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, and Preſervatives for them that with much difficulty eſcape the Taint of an ill Converſation; if but ſome of either will but kindly take what is humbly propoſed, it will be a great Reward.</p>
               <p>If I thought Healthing to be inof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive and harmleſs, I had rather a thouſand times, that the common Converſation ſhould be blameleſs, than that I ſhould blame it. And as I know it is hard rightly to reprove, ſo I know that the beſt prepared Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs are hard of digeſtion. And Men that are fond, if not proud, of a Virtue, that fits them for a general Converſation, are moſt difficultly gain'd to aſſent to any Limitations, and Reſtraint of the common Liberty, that is taken by ſome, if not moſt of every degree and quality. Dear Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of Pleaſures ſwell too big to be brought under the ſtrict Diſcipline of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53440:11"/>a good Converſation; and the grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Naughtineſs of the profuſely Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious is ſuch, that they take not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be come to Age, until they get from under the Pedagogy of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, and deride Seriouſneſs, as much as Seriouſneſs doth lament their haſte and labour to undo themſelves. Some may demand ſome expreſs divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition of drinking Healths, as if then they would not tranſgreſs it. But this Demand implies a refuſal to yield to any thing that can be ſaid, and to be ruled by any thing but what cannot be produced. But when ſuch as they will conſcienciouſly obey what is plainly written in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, they will not whet their Wits, to cut aſunder rational Connections and Conſequences from Divine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, to open a broad Path for their Luſts, and diſorderly Walking.</p>
               <p>I am not ſo fond of my own Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions and Reaſons, as to look for wonderful Effects from them; nor ſo dull, as not to foreſee what work ſome Men may make of what I write: Altho I am ſure, my Antidotes and Remedies are incomparably better than the moral Diſeaſe of Healthing,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53440:11"/>altho it had never killed its Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands. I ſhall not marvel, if this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe be toſt up and down in ſport, or kick'd up and down in Anger and Diſdain: but I will ſtill marvel, why Men call'd Chriſtians, will make void God's Laws, and caſt them behind their Backs. I will ſtill marvel, why Men, endued with ſo noble and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine a Faculty as Reaſon is, and that Reaſon ſo finely ſet in many, with a ſparkling Wit, that both ſhines and cuts, ſhould practiſe that, for which no good Reaſon was ever produced or offered. And I will not only won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but I will lament, that Men ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of immortal Glory and Honour, do ſo debaſe themſelves, as to lay their Honour in Wet &amp; Dirt, to turn their Throats into a Sink, and their Bellies into a Common-Shore Are not Men fallen out with their Maker, that deface his Image in themſelves and others by Intemperance? and are not ſatisfied with that Defacement, but proceed to deſtroy it, by cutting off their own and others Lives?</p>
               <p>The Bodies of Men are ſmall Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, richly laden with a great Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, an immortal Soul, and many
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53440:12"/>rich Gifts and Talents; they are put out in a Sea of Mercies, and favoured with a proſperous Wind, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to keep a ſtraight Courſe to the Heavenly <hi>Canaan.</hi> But, to our great grief and amazement, we ſee ſome, and hear of others very often, ſplit, and ſunk into the bottomleſs Deep of Eternity, and ſeveral diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and lie by to be carin'd. The Account of theſe unvaluable Loſſes is this in ſhort: The Owners and Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors of theſe Veſſels would not learn the ſpiritual Art of this Navigation; and whereas others that ſafely arrive, do carefully obſerve the Card and Compaſs, obey Commands, take the Wind and Seaſon, prepare for Storms and Encounters, watch and pray; theſe Extravagants obſerve no Card, keep no Compaſs, neglect the Wind, caſt off their Commander, drink down their Pilot into a deep and dead Sleep, make frequent Viſits and Invitations, treat and drink high and often. The Plague of Sin and Vice did ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, they grew diſeaſed; ſome loved their Friends to death; and others quarrelled, fought, and killed their Companions. When we
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53440:12"/>ſee and hear ſuch Miſcarriages as theſe, ſuch doleful Tidings and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of Deſtruction upon Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhall we not adviſe, warn, and importune thoſe who have yet eſcaped the Wreck, and thoſe who have not yet put out to Sea, to take heed that they periſh not by the ſame means? Who is ſo inhumane, as not to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with, and grieve for the Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Society, and the Deſtruction of Men? But which is the trueſt kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to ſtudy to prevent the Death of more, or to lament the doleful End of a vain Life of too many? The Loſs to the Living, who loſt their ſhare of Comfort and Happineſs, in the caſting away of theſe mad Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers, is not comparable to their own; and none can compute the Loſs, but they that ſuffer it, and feel it in Eternity. It is unſpeakable Folly, not to know the worth of that Treaſure they carry in them, until it is loſt in the bottom of another World; and that Men will not believe whither they are going, till they are gone for ever.</p>
               <p>The River is full of ſuch miſcarry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Veſſels, and Healthing is the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver's Mouth; at this they firſt ſet out,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53440:13"/>who never return to God, nor a ſound Mind, nor the Path of Life. I have ever obſerved, the greateſt Safety to be in keeping furtheſt off from it, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by keeping Company, or taking leave upon firm Land. It hath proved dangerous to go with Company as far as the River's Mouth; for when they are once got in, and gone one Mile in the way of Compliance, they have been towed on by the Ropes of Civility and Complement, or urged, and indeed compell'd by Importunity to go with them twain, or a great way further than they ſhould have done. And what if ſome know their own Strength? that they can ſwim with the Stream of this Cuſtom, and keep their Head above the danger of a Plunge? Yet with what quietneſs and eaſe of Spirit can they look upon their dear Friends and Companions, reeling, ſickning, falling, dying round about them! Who can deny Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be the beginning and entrance into innumerable Evils, the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of many Woes and Sorrows, too big to be concealed, and too groſs to be excuſed? The Humor ſpreads more and more, and breaks out as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53440:13"/>the Diſeaſe, an evil Diſeaſe to the Morals of this Age; and the Humor is catching, becauſe it pretends to ſome Breeding and Civility; and it is the more taking among the Vulgar, becauſe it comes from the Univerſity, and Inns of Court, from the Cities, and great Mens Houſes. And altho ſome, who are of a harder Tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Virtue, do not lie by it, nor keep Chamber, nor walk upon Crut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches for it; yet we know, the far greater Number of Healthers had preſerved much Purity in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, Sobriety in their Minds, Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency in their Hands, Health in their Bodies, and their Breath in their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, had they not drunk down theſe Potions.</p>
               <p>What St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> wrote of <hi>Apu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat Dei,</hi> l. 8. c. 14.</note> that the Title of his Book was, <hi>De Deo Socratis,</hi> but in his Book and Diſputation it ſelf he calls him <hi>Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;</hi> may be ſaid by experience of this. As the <hi>God of Socrates,</hi> in the Title of the Book, proved to be a <hi>Daemon</hi> in the Book it ſelf: ſo it is your Health in the Preface and Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of drinking; but it proves Sickneſs, Debauchery, Blows, Wounds,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53440:14"/>Death; O that I could ſtop here, and not ſay, Damnation too, in the courſe and progreſs of it!</p>
               <p>Is not a Health now become a Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of a Battel, in which many loſe their precious Lives baſely and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manely; others their Senſes, their Clothes, their Modeſty; and they who eſcape with their Lives, loſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for the time? Is not this the Belt, that makes the Union of many in Sin and Wickedneſs too great and ſtraight? And is not this the Sword, that makes the Rupture and Diſunion almoſt inourable? Is not this ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Symbol, and the Colours, the Colours of a Party? and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Defiance, and the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge? Is it not upon this, as upon a prophane Sacrament, that Men in effect vow and ſwear a Confederacy, or an Enmity? Is it not unſafe run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into this <hi>Dilemma?</hi> If you drink, you are gone; if you refuſe, you are in danger of being ſped. I am ſure this Cup is not the Cup of Bleſſing, 'tis not the Cup of the Lord. It puts many a Soul out of all preparation for death; but now who dares come within the Liſts, but he that is near
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53440:14"/>End, one way or other, be he never ſo unprepared for it? The old Form, which became a Proverb, <hi>Aut bibe, aut abi, Do as we do, or be gone,</hi> was ſafe and civil, in compariſon with the Forms of our young Maſters, who ſwear you ſhall drink, or ſwear they'll run you through, they'll ſee through you, they'll pin you to the Wall, or faſten you to the Ground. Theſe can ſacrifice to your Health, and ſend you to Hell; damn themſelves, and you too. It is dangerous to drink, and it is deadly to refuſe. O the Patience of God, and the Provocations of this kind of Murderers! Do they not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that if they are ſo bold with Death, Death will make much more bold with them? Is it a Glory to them, that they have the ability to do ſo great a Miſchief? Was it to <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi>'s Honour to kill <hi>Clytus,</hi> that had ſaved his Life, in a drunken Frenzy? What! they would be <hi>Alexanders</hi> alſo! who by being drunk, loſt the Glory which he had gotten when he was ſober, and merited the Title of <hi>Mad-Man,</hi> as well as <hi>Great,</hi> for his being a ſucceſsful Murderer or Executioner. The ſtill and private
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53440:15"/>Sot, that bibs by himſelf, that lives and dies almoſt every day; that lives a Sot, and dies an Infidel; that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes indeed there will be a Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection out of his Sleep, but ſo lives, as if there would be no Judgment, nor Reſurrection from the Dead to it; even this quiet Bibber is a vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſober Man, compared with theſe growing <hi>Alexanders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Surely it is high time to make ſome enquiry into this Diſeaſe which kills ſo faſt, and to make what diſcovery we can. And tho we cannot reform, let us not by a ſtupid or timerous ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence ſeem to allow, but rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the Enormity, diſcover the Sin and Danger which is not diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and juſtify the refuſal of drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Healths. It is a Ceremony deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtained and polluted with groſs Debauchery, and at beſt but an empty Formality, and in ſome 'tis a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and crying Sin. And if Blood cry for Vengeance, and a ſudden premature Deſtruction, by drinking Men into Diſeaſes and the Grave, be a ſecret Murder, it concerns all that do, or do not believe a Judgment to come, to abſtain from it, and all that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53440:15"/>can, to reform and forbid it. And if but ſome one or few ſhall receive any ſatisfaction and benefit by it, he that endeavoureth it ſhall never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent his Pains, tho he may be ſure to be paid off by ſome with contempt and deriſion.</p>
               <p>And notwithſtanding all manner of diſcouragements, I do, in obſervance of the many awaking Calls of divine Providence, apply my ſelf to this Subject; wiſhing, for the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the patient Reader's ſake, that my Reaſon were but equal to my Antipathy againſt Healthing, which is daily encreaſed by my fervent Love to the World, and by a Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for the many Sins and bitter Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows which begin with this kind of Complement. And I have but one Requeſt to the Reader, that he will anſwer my Affection to him with its like; and then we ſhall agree in Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, tho my Reaſon ſtand not right in his Eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:53440:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Shewing that Ceremonies and Rules of engaging to drink to exceſs, and particularly this of Healthing, hath been reproved by Ancient Fathers, and Modern Divines. How the Queſtion of drinking Healths hath been ſtated and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined.</head>
               <p n="1">§. 1. I Do acknowledg, that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived my Information of the Judgment of the Fathers, from holy and learned Mr. <hi>Rob. Bolton,</hi> in his Book called, <hi>Dinections for comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table walking with God.</hi> And ſince I have been Owner of the Books them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, I have examined the Quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and made ſome further uſe of them. And by the way, I do ſeriouſly offer this to the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of every conſciencious and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Reader:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whether, ſeeing we ought to be holy in all manner of Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for God is holy, the nearer we
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53440:16"/>come to a Strictneſs, and the further from Senſuality, and pleaſing our ſelves, to the offence and enſnaring of others, or to the emboldning of ſuch as abuſe Matters of Liberty to a Licenſe, be not more becoming a Chriſtian, and holy Walking, than an arbitrary Latitude, which may prove indulgent to the Fleſh, which all muſt crucify that hope to be ſaved?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether we owe not a greater obſervance to the Rules of holy Walking, ſuppoſing them framed according to the ſeverity of a morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Heart, and perhaps judged by ſome as too preciſe and ſtrict, than to ſuch Perſons as pleaſe their own Palates, or look more to a Civil Complement, than a Divine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment? Should I not rather follow the Directions of ſuch a <hi>Noah,</hi> as Reverend Mr. <hi>Bolton</hi> was, than the Modes of promiſcuous Company, that cannot pretend to follow any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Rule in theſe Modes and Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities? Yea, whether I owe not a greater reſpect to the Judgment and Directions of ſuch a Father as Mr. <hi>Bolton</hi> was, than (ſuppoſe) to the freer Converſation of younger
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53440:17"/>Divines, who never felt the Agonies of Conſcience he did, nor ſaw the Beauty of Holineſs which he ſaw? What tho he be dead, and they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving? he in his Grave, and in Heaven, and they at Table, and preſent? Why are ſuch Directions read, but to be remembred and practiſed? And according to the old Rule, <hi>Finge Catonem,</hi> I have often thought, when I have ſeen ſome take a liberty, what would Mr. <hi>Bolton</hi> ſay to ſuch things as theſe! Had I never had any ſtronger Reaſon for my Forbearance than this, Mr. <hi>Bolton</hi> reproved it, my Heart would have ſmitten me for a Compliance. Could I poſſibly reduce Healthing to any Commandment, or any Petition in the Lord's Prayer, I think I ſhould not ſcruple it; but that's paſt my Skill and Reach. But I think a Man may, without much ſtretching, reduce the Occaſions of Sin to that Sin, or thoſe Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which forbid the Sin.</p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. The Fathers that declaim'd and preached ſharply againſt Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, and Engagements to Exceſs, are St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> Sermon againſt Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53440:17"/>and Luxury, into which the People ran at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> to his great Sorrow. St. <hi>Auguſtine, Serm. de Tem.</hi> 232. St. <hi>Ambroſe, libro de Helia &amp; Jejunio.</hi> I acknowledg, that moſt of the vehement Paſſages in theſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, are againſt Exceſs of drinking, and ſeeking Victory by drinking, and urging to drink, <hi>ad aequales cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> a like quantity, in a like kind; and therefore come not home to this Queſtion of drinking Healths direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For 'tis acknowledged, that ſome that drink Healths, are Perſons of that Civility, that they will not urge, neither to the ſame quantity and number, nor in the ſame kind, but indulge ſome kind of Liberty. But I conceive St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaks home to Healthing, to which I ſhall ſtrictly confine my ſelf.</p>
               <p n="3">§. 3.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſtin.</hi> Serm. de Temp <hi>231</hi> Ebrietatis malum ſit grave vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, &amp; Deo odibile, ita per univerſum mundum d pluribus in conſuétudinem miſſum eſt, ut ab illis qui Dei praecepta cognoſcere nolunt, jam nec putetut eſſe peccatum.</note> The great Sin of Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs overſlows moſt Nations; and it is ſo noiſom a Sin in it ſelf, and perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in its Effects, that Men could not ordinarily ſubject themſelves to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53440:18"/>its Power, but by ſome taking and enchanting Preface. St. <hi>Baſil</hi> calls the Devil, (the great Maſter of ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous and prophane Ceremonies,) the Maker of the Laws of Drinking, in that pathetical Sermon. Men could not be commonly cheated out of their Senſes and Reaſon, but by a Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious Miſt, ſome goodly Pretence. Several Nations have had their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ways;<note place="margin">Vid Epiſt <hi>Lipſii,</hi> Centur. Miſcel. Ep. <hi>10.</hi> La <hi>Horat</hi> Od. <hi>27.</hi> &amp; <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b ni</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Soy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiſſare eſt inebriari. <hi>Cael. Rhod</hi>
                  </note> and barbarous People firſt began, and others followed. The Form of Invitation among us is a Health. Our bleſſed Saviour, who paid a great Price for the Bread we eat, and our ſmalleſt Beer, taught us to ask for our Comforts, as they that pray to do the Will of God on Earth as it is in Heaven; and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle taught us, that <hi>every Creature is ſanctified by the Word of God, and Prayer.</hi> But inſtead of Prayer, we have, <hi>Here's a Health,</hi> the Form of prophaning of Cups, and they are accordingly bleſs'd. Such Forms were unknown to the Primitive Chriſtians; but after that Chriſtians waxed fat, and abuſed the Bleſſing of Plenty, they heard of it in a ſolemn manner from their Teachers.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:53440:18"/>§. 4. St. <hi>Baſil</hi> deſcribes the Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for the drinking Combat thus:</p>
               <q>Very early they meditate and provide for their drinking; they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn their Rooms with Carpets and Hangings, they exerciſe or train up their Servants for it: They ſhew all care and diligence to provide Cups, and cooling Veſſels, Bowls and Plate, ſetting them out as in a Pomp and ſolemn Feaſt-Day, that the Variety and Fairneſs of the Veſſels may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get an Appetite, and ſtir up Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and that by the commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and change of Cups, they may drink the longer. They ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point Overſeers and Officers, the Governor of the Feaſt, Yeoman of the Wine; and after all, there is but an Order in a diſorderly and confuſed Thing. And as the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Earthly Princes is augmented by their Guards: ſo do they, by aſſigning Offices to Drunkenneſs, as to a certain Queen; they endeavour to hide the Turpitude of it, by the means of theſe Officers. And over and above, there are added Crowns, and Flowers, and Ointments, and a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53440:19"/>Thouſand ſorts of Fumes and Smells, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then the Drinking go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on, they contend to encreaſe the Madneſs, and ambitiouſly ſtrive for Drunkenneſs, as for a Victory; of which Law they have the Devil for the Author, and Sin the Reward of the Victory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When they are thought to have drunk well, they fall to drinking after the manner of Beaſts, that ſtoop down to drink out of a running Spring: For there ſtands forth a young Man, not drunk as yet, bearing upon his Shoulder a Veſſel of cooled Wine; ſtanding in the midſt, he diſtributes Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to his Gueſts through crooked Pipes. This is a new way of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring to every Man an equal ſhare, that there be no Envy, nor Grudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor Fraud, nor Cheat in drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Every one takes the Pipe or Canal that is ſet before him, and drinks at one draught as much as the Veſſel contains, out of the Silver Pipe.</q>
               <p n="5">§. 5. St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> relates the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of drinking in the likeneſs of a Battel.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:53440:19"/>You may ſee the Ranks of divers Cups, which you may imagine to be a Battel ſet in Array; Golden and Silver Veſſels ſet out, you would think it a Show. In the middle there is a Horn full of Wine, <hi>non epularis, ſed praeliaris inſtrumentum buccinae;</hi> not to ſerve as a Trumpet to call to a Feaſt, but to ſound a Battel. Firſt, they flouriſh and <hi>picqueer</hi> with ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler Cups, as in a Skirmiſh. But this is no Shew or Appearance of Sobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, but the Rule of Drinking. For as Actors of Tragedies do ſenſibly and by degrees raiſe their Voice, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til they have opened the Paſſage for a lively Voice, that afterwards they may make the place ring with the greater Noiſe: So they do at firſt exerciſe themſelves with preluſory Cups, to provoke to a Thirſt, leſt perchance they quench it, and being ſatiated, they may afterwards drink no more. When they are warm, they call for greater Cups: Then the Heat grows to a Flame. Dry Meat grows hot with Thirſt; and as the Veſſels begin to be low, they are fill'd up with purer or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixed Drink. Cups contend with
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53440:20"/>Meat, and betwixt whiles they are often doubled. Then the Drinking being protracted, there are great ſtrifes and contendings who ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell (exceed) in drinking. <hi>Nota gravis;</hi> It is a diſgrace or a diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to a Man, if he excuſe himſelf, or if a Man think it would do well to temper the Wine. And thus they do till they come to the ſecond Courſe or Service. But as ſoon as the Banquet is done, and you would think they muſt riſe, then do they again renew their Drink. And when they have done all, then they ſay they do but begin. Then the Golden Pots are carried, and the greater Goblets, as ſo many Inſtruments of War. And leſt this be thought immoderate and exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, there is a meaſure made, and the ſtrife is before a Judg, and it is determined by a Law. The <hi>Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothetes,</hi> or Maſter of theſe Games and Revels there, is Fury, the Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend is Debility, the Reward of the Victory is Fault, the Event of the War is uncertain a great while. — Theſe are the the only Strifes that are inexcuſable. If a Man in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53440:20"/>War finds himſelf too weak, he turns his Arms, and deſerves a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don; but here, if any Man gives up, or turns his Cup, he is urged to drink. If where you ſtrive for Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, any Man lift you up with his hand, you loſe the Garland, but you are free from ſuffering Injury thereby: In your Banquets, if a Man take off his hand from the Wine, it is poured into his Mouth. All are drunk; the Conquerors and Conquered do all lie down drunk, and very many aſleep. Neither is it lawful to carry any of them to their Grave, before he that feedeth them, hath ſeen Vengeance done to them all, that he may revenge his Expence upon them. — A moſt doleful Spectacle to the Eyes of Chriſtians, a moſt miſerable Show! <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe de Helia &amp; Jejunio,</hi> cap. 13.</bibl>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quid obteſtationes potantium loquar? quid memorem ſacramenta, quae violare nefas arbitrantur? Bibamus inquiunt, pro ſalute Imperatorum.</hi> 
                  <q>To what purpoſe ſhall I ſpeak of thoſe moſt earneſt Intreaties? wherefore ſhould I remember thoſe Sacraments (or Oaths) which it is unlawful to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53440:21"/>violate? Let us drink for the Health of the Emperors. <bibl>
                        <hi>Idem, cap.</hi> 17, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="6">§. 6. I will forbear to produce the Sayings of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in this place, referring him to ſome following Heads; nor will I be large in Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations out of modern Divines, who have reproved this exorbitant Humor of the Times, as Reverend Mr. <hi>Bolton</hi> calls it. Read him if you pleaſe, <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for walking with God,</hi> p. 200. What ſaith the moſt learned Mr. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Gataker</hi> to it? Hear him. <hi>Alſo to let paſs the brutiſh and ſwiniſh Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of thoſe that think there is no true Welcome, nor good Fellowſhip, as they term it, unleſs there be deep carouſing of Healths to the Bride and Bridegroom, and every idle Fellows Miſtreſs, till the whole Companies Wits be drown'd in Drink, that not Religion only, but Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it ſelf be wholly exil'd, and the Meeting it ſelf be rather call'd a drunken Match, than a Marriage-Feaſt.</hi> This Vehemence is not uſual in that great Man, but it ſeems the Matter moved him. Epiſt before Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi>'s Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, called the <hi>Marriage-Feaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Read, if you would ſee and read,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53440:21"/>what's convincingly and perſuaſively written by that attractive and divine Preacher, Dr. <hi>Robert Harris,</hi> in his <hi>Drunkards Cup, Folio, pag.</hi> 307, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Ingenious and Reverend Mr. <hi>Sam. Ward</hi> of <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> gives Examples of ſix or ſeven, that ſoon died after their drinking Healths, by means thereof; and preſcribes, as the beſt means againſt ruining <hi>Drunkenneſs,</hi> if great Perſons would firſt begin tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Reformation in their own Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, baniſh the Spirits of their But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, abandon that fooliſh and vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Cuſtom, as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> and <hi>Baſil</hi> call it, of drinking Healths, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that a <hi>Sacrifice to God</hi> for the Health of others, which is rather a Sacrifice to the Devil, and a Bane of their own. In his Sermon called, <hi>Wo to Drunkards,</hi> p. 537, &amp; 553 of the <hi>Collection of his Sermons.</hi> That excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Expoſitor of the <hi>Canticles</hi> and <hi>Revelations,</hi> Mr. <hi>James Durham</hi> of <hi>Glaſcow</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> in his Expoſition of the Commandments, <hi>Com.</hi> 7. ſaith, <hi>That drinking of Healths, and pledging, is one of the higheſt Provocations in Drunkenneſs, and dreadful perverting the End for which God hath given Meat and I rink,</hi> p. 390.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:53440:22"/>That very judicious and zealous Divine, Mr. <hi>Rich. Garbut,</hi> (Author of that <hi>full and excellent Demonſtration of the Reſurrection,</hi> much and very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly commended) falls heavy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Sin of Drunkenneſs,</hi> and with a keen edg, in a homely, but methinks majeſtick Northern Dialect, ſtrikes at Healthing, to ſtrike the Cup out of his Hand, and the Sin out of his Heart. <hi>The Drunkard, Devil-like,</hi> (O read and fear, fear and abhor, abhor with Repentance) <hi>is a Sinner, who cannot be content to be wicked alone, but he muſt needs tempt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to the ſame Wickedneſs alſo. Do not Healths, and whole ones, and putting the Cup to the Noſe, and down the Throat, or down the Neck, look for it? And will you not do me right?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>One come from the Dead, to awaken Drunkards and Whoremongers.</hi> The ſubſtance of ſome. <hi>Sermons</hi> of his, <hi>p.</hi> 70, <hi>&amp; alibi.</hi> I have heard, that worthy Mr. <hi>John Geree</hi> hath written a Tract on purpoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Healthing.</p>
               <p n="7">§. 7. Theſe were the Thoughts of thoſe eminently learned and holy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of this Mode. And certainly
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53440:22"/>they were Men as like to know Good and Evil, as moſt Men were in their days, or that now ſurvive them. And when I ſee but one Preacher or Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, of their Piety and Learning, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Lawfulneſs or Innocency of Healthing, I will encreaſe my Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but hardly abate my Prejudice, or forſake my Reaſon. I know it is very common and faſhionable among the Clergy; but whether ever they found comfort in it, or durſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and approve of it, I leave to their conſideration. Surely thoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, that have ſtudied the Word of God, that preached moſt zealouſly to the ſalvation of Souls; that were neareſt Heaven in a holy Life, and moſt above the Preferments, and Complaiſance, as the way to them, were moſt to be attended to. It ſeems not to be once ſcrupled by very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or they would not be ſo officious and forward. But to avoid the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of <hi>Singularity,</hi> and to ſhew that there is matter of Conſcience in it, I will, in the next place, ſhew how the Caſe hath been ſtated and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:53440:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Shewing how the Queſtion of drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Healths hath been ſtated and reſolved, with ſome Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions upon it.</head>
               <p n="1">§. 1. THe famous Philoſopher and Divine, <hi>Mar. Trider. Wen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delinus, Philoſophiae moralis lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 16. propounds the Queſtion thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quaeritur an per ſobrietatem liceat, in alterius ſalutem bibere?</hi> Whether it conſiſt not with Sobriety, to drink the Health (or to the Health) of another?</p>
               <p>After he hath ſhewed it was the ancient Cuſtom of the <hi>Greeks, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, Germans,</hi> and <hi>Muſcovites,</hi> he reſolves the Queſtion in the Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, <hi>but with a Limitation:</hi> It is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to drink to the Health of another; <hi>quatenus fieri id nullo ſobrietatis detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento poteſt,</hi> as far as it may be done without the harm or detriment of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety; for we may teſtify our Joy of anothers Health by this Sign, as
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53440:23"/>well as by any other Sign. The ſence of this Queſtion, propounded in this form, is no more but this, That one may drink to anothers Helth, and be ſober. But as thus reſolved, it gives no countenance to the common practice of Healthers. And tho it may conſiſt with Sobriety, if it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt not with another Grace, or Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, or Duty, or with Prayer to God, which is implied in it, or it ſignifies nothing, it may be unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
               <p>But ſaith he, <hi>Quod ſi vero propinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis intentio ſit: But if it be the Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him that drinks, to overwhelm others, with Cups to the Health of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and to thruſt them down, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne them from the ſtate of a ſound Mind; and the Intention of the Pledger be to fulfil the deſire of him that drinks or begins to him, as it is in</hi> Germany <hi>and</hi> Muſcovy, <hi>we</hi> embrace and hold the Negative, <hi>for this manifeſt reaſon, becauſe we are all bound to ſtudy Sobriety.</hi> Luke 21.34. 1 Pet. 3.7. &amp; 5.8. <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitent hoc,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Aulae &amp; Aulici,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Let Princes Courts, and Courtiers think of this, who ſo drink the Healths of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that they hazard and impair their own.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:53440:24"/>It may well be doubted, whether they who lead and follow in this Maze of Healthing, will thank this learned Man for determining in favour of them. Do they not venture, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out asking Queſtions for Conſcience<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake? and make a common Treſpaſs and Path, where the Author of our Salvation hath raiſed a Wall, with a Caveat, <hi>Take beed leſt any of you be overcharged with Surfeiting and Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs,</hi> &amp;c.? Here's ſmall Thanks to be paid to <hi>Wendeline</hi> for his Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, except he had taken away the Reſtriction.</p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. Our acute Schoolman, and conciſe Caſuiſt, Dr. <hi>Ames,</hi> is round and quick in dehorting from all the Rites and Sacraments of <hi>Bacchus: Abſtinendum eſt igitur,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Therefore we muſt abſtain, (even from this ground, if there were no other) from all thoſe Rites by which Drunkenneſs is wont arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially to be promoted: Of which kind are Adjurations of others,</hi> by great Names,<note place="margin">i. e. Hëalths.</note> or the Names of ſuch as are dear, <hi>to empty Cups; the ſending about of Cups to be taken off by all alike; the Abuſe of Lots, (as they uſe in ſome
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53440:24"/>Places by Dice put into a Jug or cup, inſtead of a Rattle, or by a Mill affixed to a Jug or Pot) according to a fictitious Law (not written) and laying a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon the Gueſts: And from all other the like Myſteries of</hi> Bacchus, <hi>and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuductions to Exceſs of Drinking.</hi> Caſe Conſc. lib. 3. cap. 16.</p>
               <p n="3">§. 3. The deep-ſighted, ſearching, and skilful Guide of Souls, in all the paths of a holy and righteous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, Mr. <hi>R. B.</hi> in his volumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Treaſure of practical Doctrines, the <hi>Chriſtian Directory,</hi> puts the Caſe, and reſolves it thus:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> Is it not lawful to drink a Health ſometimes, when it would be ill taken to refuſe it, or to be unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered while others drink it?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Diſtinguiſh between drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing meaſurably, as you need it, and unmeaſurably, when you need it not. 2. Between the foreſeen Effects, and doing it ordinarily, or when it would do hurt, or extraordinarily, when it will more prevent hurt. And ſo I conclude;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It is unlawful to drink more than is good for your Health, by
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53440:25"/>the provocation of other Men.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It is unlawful to do that which tempteth and encourageth others to drink too much. And ſo doth the Cuſtom of pledging Healths, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when it is taken for a Crime to deny it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">☞</note> The ordinary drinking and pledging of ſuch Healths is unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, becauſe it is the ſcandalous hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of others in their Sin, unto their Ruine.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. But if we fall among ſuch <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Beaſts,</hi> as would ſtab a Man, if he would not drink a Health, it is lawful to do it to ſave ones Life, as it is to give a Thief my Purſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not a thing ſimply evil in it ſelf, to <hi>drink that Cup,</hi> but <hi>by Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident,</hi> which a greater Accident may preponderate.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Therefore any other Accident, beſide the loſing of your Life, which will really preponderate the hurtful Accident, may make it lawful: As poſſibly in ſome Caſes and Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, the Offence given by denying it, may be ſuch as will do more hurt far than yielding would do; (as if a malignant Company would lay
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:53440:25"/>ones Loyalty to the King upon it.)</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Chriſtian Prudence therefore (without carnal compliance) muſt be always the preſent Decider of the Caſe, by comparing the good and evil Effects.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. To be bare, when others lay the Honour of the King or Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors upon it, is a Ceremony, that on the aforeſaid reaſon may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied with.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. When to avoid a greater Evil, we may <hi>extraordinarily</hi> be put to any ſuch Ceremony, it is meet that we join ſuch Words, (where we have liberty) as may prevent the Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, or hardning any Perſon in Sin.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. And it is our Duty to avoid the Company that will put us upon ſuch Inconveniencies, as far as our Calling will allow.</p> 
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Chriſt. Direct. Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>fol.</hi> 388.</bibl>
               </q>
               <p n="4">§. 4. Upon the Reſolution of the Caſe ſo ſtated, by this eminent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of Chriſt, I will be bold to make ſome Obſervations.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:53440:26"/>I obſerve three Things in the Caſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Is it lawful ſometimes to drink a Health? By this the common Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice is ſhut out of the queſtion, as an unlawful Cuſtom, as he plainly ſpeaks.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When it will be ill taken to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, and then when a Man cannot without danger put it by; intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that a Man ſhould do what he can to avoid it. And if a Man muſt do what he can to avoid it, it is clearly a thing unlawful to urge it, and worſe to take the refuſal ill. The Suppoſition in the Caſe is this; That a ſober Man may fall into ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, that are ſo unreaſonable and uncivil, as to take it ill that any ſhould refuſe to do as they would have him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Ceremony of being unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered when Healths are drunk, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother part of the Caſe, and inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, That a ſober Man may well ſcruple to conform ſo far.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:53440:26"/>4. If it be unlawful to drink more than will do a Man good, by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation or urgency of another; then it is manifeſtly unlawful to call upon, or urge a Man to drink; and he that urgeth another, is not a fit Judg of the Harm, but he that knows his own Neceſſity and Strength.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Drinking and pledging Healths, in a cuſtomary way, is to tempt and encourage to Exceſs, and ſo it's a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ſcandalous thing, hardning of Men to their Ruine.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And here ariſeth another Caſe: What if a Man fall among thoſe fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Beaſts, that will ſtab a Man if he will not drink a Health? what's to be done in ſuch a caſe? It is not ſimply evil in it ſelf to drink <hi>that Cup,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>B.</hi> but by Accident, which a greater Accident may preponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. Where note, that ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that ſtand upon thoſe Terms, have put off Civility and Manhood, and are to be avoided like furious Beaſts. Yet here, I conceive, ſome Things are to be thought of in ſuch a caſe.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:53440:27"/>(1.) A Man, in caſe of danger to his Life, may drink that <hi>Cup,</hi> which they that require it call a <hi>Health,</hi> tho not in the ſame Notion and Formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in which it was urged and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) But what if the Cup be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful in it ſelf? What if a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant fall into the Company of furious Papiſts? or if a ſober Perſon fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Company of raging Hectors? And he be required to drink to the coming in of Popery, or to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and Damnation of all Whigs, or of ſuch as are hated, by any other Name? what ſhall a Man do in ſuch a Caſe? Or what if I be required to drink to the deſtruction of one, whom I am bound to love and honour? The Cup, with ſuch an Inſcription or Title, is flatly unlawful. Or what if I be required to drink to the Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Succeſs, long Life of an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to God, Religion, and my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try? Such Cups, under thoſe Titles, are to be abhorred, as ſinful. And many ſuch have been drunk in our days, full of the Poyſon of deadly Hatred. For ought I ſee, by theſe Reſolutions of enquiring Men into
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:53440:27"/>the Rules of Practice, the moſt inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent is dangerous and ſcandalous.</p>
               <p>Here's enough to direct ſober Men, that deſire to walk by a Rule; yet the Queſtion is capable of Enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and I ſhall preſent what I have found out upon enquiry.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:53440:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Some Things premiſed. In what Notion Healthing is taken. That Healthing is ancient, is no Plea for it. Liberty of drinking more ancient. A Sacrifice and Prayer, or honorary, memorative Sign, by <hi>Ambroſe, Auguſtine, Roſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> &amp;c. Its Riſe. Its Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to us.</head>
               <p n="1">§. 1. ANd here I muſt premiſe:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That it is ſuſpicious, that the Ceremony of Healthing did ſpring from the ſame Original that other Ceremonies of drinking did, and to the ſame End of Intemperance, and fatal Corruption of true Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and good Society. And if this were doom'd by common Conſent to Oblivion, it would not be long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore another ſhould be brought into its place, as long as Men are prone to that Sin which is the diſgrace of Mankind. But then, if there be any Reverence for our Maker, any Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:53440:28"/>to our excellent Nature, Men ſhould ſtop every Door at which Sin enters, by the Devil's Inſtruction, in a diſguiſe, to bind us, and then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Rational Men ſhould not require clearer or ſtronger Arguments againſt Healthing, than the Subject will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford. It is not to be doubted, but if Healthing were as expreſly forbidden, as Murther or Fornication, but it would be a dark and controverted Text to ſome, which is as clear as the Sun to others, and it would be practiſed for all the Prohibition.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Tho all the Converſation of Chriſtians ſhould be Chriſtian, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Laws of Chriſt, and of entire Charity and Benevolence, and therefore above that which is meerly Civil; yet it is lawful to converſe with Men in the generality of human Nature, upon good occaſions, and for good ends. It is our duty to communicate the good Things which Divine Bounty hath beſtowed upon us; and it is our duty, to expreſs our mutual Eſteem and Affections by Words or Deeds: and ſo it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful at our Tables, and other Meetings,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:53440:29"/>to drink one to another, as it is to help or carve, or to invite them to a liberty to partake of what we have. And it may become us to remember our abſent Friends, and that when we meet as Confederates in the ſame Covenant of Grace, in the ſame Religion, Name, Nature, and Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. The diſtaſte is not only againſt this Ceremony, but any other, that doth tacitely or expreſly lay any ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation upon any Man to drink for his carnal pleaſure or harm.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Mutual, ſober, communicative Drinking, is an expreſſion of a Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Confederacy; and therefore it is not unlawful for one to expreſs that Friendſhip and Love by Words or Signs. I may wiſh him any Grace or Mercy from God. But when that which is intended, is the gratification of the Fleſh, and the Health is but a pretence for it, it cannot be excuſed nor defended.</p>
               <p n="6">6. There is a great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween drinking a Health, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring of a Friend in drinking, both in the intention of the thing, and common practice; but if the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:53440:29"/>remembrance of the abſent be any kind of engagement to drink unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably, or exceſſively, it is as bad as Healthing. But there is a great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between them: The one is profitable, and the other not; the one is a Duty, the other not; for the one we have divine Precedents, for the other none. When we call to mind our abſent Friends, we make them as perſonally preſent as we can; we include them in the ſame Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the preſent: We remember their condition and circumſtances of Life, and ſo according to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition we are affected, ſometimes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Joy and Thankſgivings, ſometimes into Pity and Commiſeration, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times into Sorrow and Sympathy. It was the Sin of them that drank Wine in Bowls, that they forgat the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of <hi>Joſeph. Amos</hi> 1. And it was an effectual way to forget him. Remembrance of the Abſent may move us to weep and ſigh, and to forbear our drinking, may afford matter of Diſcourſe, and to lay aſide our Cups: But in Healthing, what is there more than drinking our ſelves, and making others drink, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:53440:30"/>that to the preſent, as well or more than the abſent.</p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. That which I am enquiring into, is drinking a Health or Healths, abſtracted from the Formalities of being uncovered, or kneeling, or any other Accident or Effects, but in it ſelf, as near as I can. It is the firſt Occaſion and Spring of much Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Sin, and Evil; it ſendeth out both the ſweet of ſuch Kindneſs as it is, and the bitter of Unkindneſs; it is an implicit Prayer, if not expreſs, and a Curſe. It is to the Happineſs and Unhappineſs, good Succeſs and bad, to a good Voyage, to a good Journey, to a next merry Meeting; and it is to all that is bad and fearful. The ſwaggering Proteſtant drinks it to the deſtruction of the Pope, and he is the never the further off for that; and the fiery Papiſt, he drinks the Confuſion of Hereticks. It is a Dedication, and an Execration, and ſometimes a Memorial.</p>
               <p>And I think it is a Sacrifice, or ſome kind of Sacrament, or a Prayer.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:53440:30"/>§. 3 The moſt conſiderable Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or Apology for it, is taken from its Antiquity and Univerſality, and will prove it as lawful, as the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church to be true. May not as much be ſaid for the groſſeſt of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? Sin was in the World a long time before it; this came not in, but till after the Devil grew genteel and complemental. It was an ancient Cuſtom to drink in honour of great Names, or to the Health of Friends; but to engage and challenge by it, to the infringement of Liberty and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, was unknown to the moſt ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Ages, that retained the ſhape of Humanity, and face of Vertue. This Faſhion was not come up in the days of <hi>Homer,</hi> as the Learned Dr. <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</hi> obſerves upon that Verſe of <hi>Homer:</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                     <l>At hand a Cup of Wine there ſtood,</l>
                     <l>To drink when he himſelf thought good.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:53440:31"/>
                  <hi>Nondum quippè inoleverat barbarus ille mos, provocando ſe mutuò majoribus poculis.</hi> That barbarous way of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual provocation to quaff, was then a Stranger; every Man drunk what he pleaſed, and not at the beck and guſt of other Men. He recites ſeveral Greek Authors for his Opinion, and among other Teſtimonies, a Laco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick Apothegm out of <hi>Plutarch.</hi> The <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> heard, that ſome at their Feaſting were compelled to drink, <hi>Why not,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to eat? Et certè,</hi> ſaith the Doctor, <hi>videtur eſſe par ratio, hoc eſt planè nulla:</hi> As good reaſon ſurely for the one as the other, which is none at all. — <hi>Gnomol. Homeric. Od</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 185. But after that Corruption grew rank in the Soil of Proſperity, it became pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbial of quaffing and urging, <hi>Graeco more bibere, Graeco more potare, interpretantur quidam, grandibus mera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> poculis ſe invitare.</hi> Cicero <hi>in</hi> Verrem, <hi>Action.</hi> 3. <hi>Fit ſermo inter cos, &amp; invitatio, ut Graeco more bibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur, hoſpes hortatur, poſcunt majori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus poculis, celebratur omnium ſermone laetitiâ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> convivium.</hi> Cael. Rhodigin. <hi>Antiq. Lectionum, l.</hi> 28. <hi>c.</hi> 6.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:53440:31"/>And one of their Laws of drinking, became a Proverb, <hi>Aut bibat, aut abeat;</hi> It was the ſafer way to be gone, than ſtay; for the reaſon which <hi>Cicero</hi> gives in the <hi>5th</hi> of his <hi>Tuſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan. Q. Ne ſobrius in Violentiam Vino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentorum incidat:</hi> leſt the Wine-drinkers fall upon him with Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</p>
               <p>This was a more genteel and civil Law than that, If he will not drink, pour it upon his Head; which was done to <hi>Empedocles,</hi> and which he took at a Feaſt, in ſuch Indignation, that the day following he call'd a Council, and the maker of the Feaſt, and the <hi>Sympoſiarch,</hi> or the Governour of it, were both condemned. <hi>Vid. Adag. Eraſmi, Chiliad.</hi> 1. <hi>Cent.</hi> 2. <hi>Prov.</hi> 47. <hi>Diogen. Laertius in vit. Empedoc.</hi> l. 8. <q>But our <hi>Germans,</hi> ſaith <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> are more barbarous than the <hi>Scythians:</hi> Drink, ſay they, or I will break your Head with this Jug, as big as it is.</q> The <hi>Scythians,</hi> both Men and Women, were wont to pour out Wine upon their Cloaths, account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it a pleaſant and happy Life. <hi>Quid ais? &amp; agnoſcis haec in noſtris Moribus?</hi> ſaith <hi>Lipſius.</hi> Our Bibbers
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:53440:32"/>in our Country, will pour Wine into the Boſom of them that refuſe to drink, and when they greedily drink, drop it upon their own. <hi>Lipſ. Ep. Miſcellan. Ep.</hi> 7. <hi>La.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">§. 4. The Ancient <hi>Romans</hi> uſed freedom in their drinking, without Arts of alluring. <hi>Aulus Gellius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of <hi>Romulus,</hi> the firſt King of the <hi>Romans,</hi> being invited to a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, drank but ſparingly, becauſe he had Buſineſs to do the next day; they ſaid to him, <hi>Romulus,</hi> If all Men ſhould do as you do, Wine would be cheap: He anſwered, Yea, but, it would be dearer, if every Man may drink as much as he pleaſe, for I have drunk as much as I had a mind to. <hi>A. Gell. Nect. Attic.</hi> l. 11. c. 14. The <hi>Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> alſo were very abſtemious, ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and laborious in the firſt Ages; but in proceſs of time, being infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the <hi>Median</hi> and <hi>Lybian</hi> Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, their Luſts grew corpulent and bulky, and became to be <hi>merobibos, &amp; multobibos;</hi> and they were wont to compel to drinking at their Feaſts, which made <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> to reform that evil Cuſtom, and conſtrain no Man, but indulge every Man to drink as
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:53440:32"/>little as he would. <hi>Breſſon. de Regio Perſarum Principatu,</hi> l. 2. p. 215.</p>
               <p n="5">§. 5. So it was of old, but you know how it is now. I have thought it to be ſome kind of Pagan Sacrifice, and to imply a Prayer, which are the Notions I ſhall ſtick to, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce conſiderable Proof of it. It is alſo an Honorative and Memorative Rite and Ceremony.</p>
               <p n="6">§. 6. And ſo it was taken to be by ancient Fathers, who preached and wrote againſt it, as a Sin of their times, and an Obligation to Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs: Wherefore ſhould I ſpeak of your earneſt Entreaties, and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations? Wherefore ſhould I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member your Sacraments? <hi>Quid memorem Sacramenta?</hi> your Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Oaths or Myſteries? <hi>Bibamus, inquiunt, pro Salute Imper atorum:</hi> Let us drink for the Health of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and he who refuſeth, <hi>reus erit in Devotione,</hi> he is faulty in his Devotion, Loyalty, or Love to the Emperor — <hi>O pia Devotionis Obſequium!</hi> O the ſupple flattering obſervance of pious Devotion! — Let us drink, ſay
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:53440:33"/>they, for the Health of our Armies, for the Strength and Valour of our Companions, for the Health of our Sons.— And they do think that theſe their Prayers and Vows do reach, or come up even to God; even as they who bring their Cups to the Sepulchres of the Martyrs, and there drink, <hi>in Veſperam,</hi> until the Evening, and believe, that otherwiſe they cannot be heard. <hi>O Stultitiam Hominum, qui Ebrietatem Sacrificium put ant!</hi> &amp;c. O the Folly of Men who think Drunkenneſs to be a Sacrifice! Who think them to be appeaſed with Drunkenneſs, who taught us to bear Sufferings with Faſting. <hi>Quot de In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temper antiâ convivii novimus ad Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a veniſſe?</hi> How many intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Men have we ever known to be Martyrs? —It is plain that St. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> took this Healthing to be Vows, Prayers, Sacriſice. <hi>Libr. de Helia &amp; Jejunio,</hi> c. 17.</p>
               <p n="7">§. 7. St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> in his 64 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> to Biſhop <hi>Aurelius,</hi> falls ſharply upon Drunkenneſs, and eſpecially at the Sepulchres of the Martyrs; which becauſe the carnal and ignorant Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:53440:33"/>are wont to believe to be not only the Honours of the Martyrs, but the Comforts of the dead. It ſeems to me that that Turpitude be eaſier diſſuaded from, if it be forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den out of the Scripture, and if Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and Sacrifices for the Dead, which we may truly believe to help little, upon theſe Commemorations be not ſo ſumptuous, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Roſinus</hi> confirms the Obſervation of drinking in honour of Perſons, and ſacrificing: <hi>Solemne hoc erat, ut Divo alicui libarent;</hi> and threw upon the Table or Floor ſome of their Wine, <hi>ut<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in Dominae aut Amicae Honorem Cyathum ebiberent, eam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> palàm nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narent;</hi> and then drank in honour of their Lady, Miſtreſs, or Miſs, and named her openly. <hi>Antiquitat. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manorum,</hi> l. 5. c. 30.</p>
               <p n="8">§. 8. We may learn out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Authors, that to Health is as much as to ſacrifice and pray. <q>Some, ſaith <hi>Alexander ab Alexandro,</hi> do ſay, that <hi>Graeco more bibere,</hi> to drink after the manner of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> is as often as they name or call their Gods or Friends among their Cups,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:53440:34"/>every one by his Name, ſo often to drink largely and take off their Wine; and when Magiſtrates were choſen, or Honours conferred, they carried about Wine in Goblers, and pointed them out by Name, to whom they ſhould give the Cup; and then firſt they were wont to call their Gods, and afterwards their Friends, and ſo often to drink deep, <hi>&amp; bona à Diis precari,</hi> and to beg good things of their Gods.</q> It was the Cuſtom of the <hi>Thracians, inter Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>las &amp; Porula primum libare Diis D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pes, &amp; benè precari convivis:</hi> they firſt offered Dainties to their Gods, and then pray'd for their Gueſts, and according to their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to eat their Dainties with Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, <hi>hund xliter,</hi> no otherwiſe than if it had been at a ſacred Banquet. Let them among us take notice of this, who ſit down, and riſe from their Tables, and never pray for God's Bleſſing, nor return God Thanks: And let them alſo learn from the <hi>Thracians,</hi> that pray before Meat, to eat and drink according to their Prayer, as at a holy Feaſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:53440:34"/>The <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> in their familliac eating together, pieces of the Meat and ſome Wine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thrown into the Fire, they gave Drink-Offerings to their Gods, and the firſt Fruits of their Suppers to their familiar Spirits, or Houſhold-Gods, to whom the Salt and Bread, and Cheeſe fell for their Meſs. The firſt Cup was mineled to <hi>Jupiter O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lympius,</hi> the ſecond to their Hero's, the third to <hi>Jupiter</hi> the Saviour.— And when pure, or Wine unmixed was given, it was obſerved that they ſhould call to <hi>Jovem ſoſpitem, Jupiter</hi> that giveth Health, <hi>No cemulentes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret,</hi> leſt the Wine ſhould make them drunk; but when it was mixed with Water, <hi>Jovom appellare Servato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem,</hi> to call to <hi>Jupiter</hi> the Saviour. <hi>Alex. ab Alex. Genialium Dierum,</hi> l. 5. c. 19.</p>
               <p>The third Cup was by the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents accounted ſolemn and myſtical, and it became a Cuſtom to facrifice, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the third to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter Soter.</hi> Dr. <hi>Duport. Gnomot. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi> p. 138. <hi>Vid. &amp; Coelium Rhodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginum.</hi> l. 28. c. 6. <hi>de tertio Poculo Jovi Soteri,</hi> p. 1068.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:53440:35"/>
                  <hi>Paulus in Perſa, &amp; in Sticho</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes the manner of feaſting. <hi>Toxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> calls thus;
<q>
                     <l>—Hoe age, accumbe, hunc Diem ſuavem,</l>
                     <l>Meum natalem agitemus, amaenum.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <q>Mind your Buſineſs, ſit down, let us keep this ſweet and pleaſant Day, this is my Birth-day. <hi>Age Puer,</hi> Come Boy, do thy Buſineſs, <hi>à ſummo ſeptenis Cyathis committe hos Ludos:</hi> Begin theſe Sports, or Merriments, with ſeven Cups, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning with him that ſits upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt: Be nimble, and make haſte. <hi>Pegnium,</hi> Thou doſt not give me my Cups faſt enough: Prethee give 'em me.</q>
               <q>
                  <hi>Benè mihi, benè vobis, benè Amicae meae.</hi>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>All Happineſs to me this is, a Health to you is this;</l>
                  <l>A happy Life to me, to you, and to my Friend and Miſs.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:53440:35"/>
                  <hi>Coelius Rhodiginus</hi> hath collected, That it was the Cuſtom of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> after Supper to drink <hi>Poculum boni Daemonis,</hi> the Cup of the good De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, which <hi>Euſtachius</hi> upon <hi>Homer</hi> thought to be Fortune. And what was this Cup, but a Libation or Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to Fortune? And the Cups bore the Names of their Gods, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were dedicated to them. The firſt Cup was to <hi>Jupiter Olympius,</hi> (as you heard before) the next was the Cup of the Hero's of the Earth, the third was of <hi>Jupiter</hi> the Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
               <p>But why was it called the Cup of <hi>Jupiter</hi> the Saviour? becauſe that manner of drinking was kept within the bounds of Sobriety; he that went beyond that, was noted to be intemperate. The ſame Cup was called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, from the Perfection of the number Three, which contains the Beginning, Middle, and End. It is found in Books, ſaith the ſame laborious Collector, that the chief Cup in Feaſts offered <hi>Praefatione</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. This is the Cup of the good Demon, which many thought to be <hi>Bacchus, Laetitiae Dator,</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:53440:36"/>the Giver of Mirth. The laſt was <hi>Praefations Jovis,</hi> the Cup of <hi>Jupiter Liberator,</hi> the Deliverer. We have found in <hi>Theſautis Julii Pollucis,</hi> the laſt Cup was called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curie;</hi> for riſing from Supper, they were wont to drink or ſacrifice to <hi>Mercurius,</hi> the Preſident of Sleep, as <hi>Athanaeus</hi> writes, the laſt was the Cup of <hi>Jupiter</hi> the perfect. <hi>Antiq. Leet.</hi> p. 1008.</p>
               <p>How like to theſe Paganiſh Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, are the Forms and Inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or Dedications of Health? Do they not call the Cups by the Names of the Perſons whoſe Health they drink, <hi>viz.</hi> This is your Health, ſuch a Health, have you had this Health? and when at a loſs, they ask, Whoſe Health is this? How like is this form of Speech to the old one, <hi>Bibamus pro Salute Imperatoris,</hi> let us drink for the Health of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</p>
               <p n="9">§. 9. That Healthing implies Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice and Prayer, may be proved by plainer Evidence yet, in the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and Feſtival obſerved in Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Anna Perenna,</hi> or to vary a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:53440:36"/>little after the Popiſh Dialect, the Feaſt of St. <hi>Ann Perenna.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Month of <hi>March,</hi> ſome ſay on the Ides, or 15th day of that Month, was the Feaſt of <hi>Anna,</hi> Siſter of <hi>Dido,</hi> as ſome ſay, prefer'd into the place of a Goddeſs. <hi>Eodem Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe &amp; publicè &amp; privatim, ad Annam Perennam Sacrificatum itur, ut annare &amp; perennare commodè lieas,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crobius Saturnal.</hi> l. 1. c. 12. <hi>Quò com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modius annare, &amp; perennare liceret.</hi> ſaith <hi>Alexand. ab Alexandro,</hi> l. 3. c. 18. <hi>Annare dicimus, Annum agere,</hi> to live a Year, <hi>quemadmodùm poren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare Annos peragere,</hi> to live out, or compleat many Years. <hi>Annum perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, &amp; quaſi perpetuùm agere,</hi> to live perpetually; as <hi>Peret, in Cornucopia in Martial. Epiſt.</hi> fol. 143. Col. 2. <hi>Sunt qui Lunant putarint, quae Anna vocare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quod Annus ex Menſibus fiaet. Lil. Gyraldus Syntagm. Hiſtor. Deorum Syntagm.</hi> 1. p. 57.</p>
               <p>On the Ides of <hi>March</hi> there was a Feaſt to <hi>Anna Perens, in quo largiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Poculis indulgebant, &amp; pro Cyatho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum numero Annos mutuò precabantur;</hi> in which they gave themſelves to drink larger Cups than ordinary;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:53440:37"/>and according to the number of the Cups, they pray'd for ſo many Years to live for one another. <hi>Roſin. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitat. Roman.</hi> l. 4. <hi>Calendario Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano;</hi> which Feaſt is deſcribed by <hi>Ovid. Faſtor. Libr.</hi> 3.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sole tamen, Vino<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> calent, Annoſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> precantur;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quot ſumunt Cyathos, ad numerum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> bibunt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Invenies illic qui Neſtoris ebibat Annos.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>Well warm'd with Sun and Wine, for Years they wiſh,</l>
                  <l>For every Year they wiſh, they take a Diſh,</l>
                  <l>(They drink and pray) and to a number drink:</l>
                  <l>Some to the Years of <hi>Neſtor</hi> e're they ſhrink.</l>
               </q>
               <p>To conclude this Evidence, that Healthing doth intimate a Sacrifice or Prayer, may appear from that horrid, and worſe than barbarous, that cruel and deviliſh Sin of impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating Evil to Enemies in their Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of drinking, when they wiſh, till
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:53440:37"/>they curſe even to Hell; therefore when they are pleaſed, then it is your Health, the beſt Prayer they can make. This is a Jewiſh Cuſtom at their Weddings, when they drink and pledg, they ſay, <hi>Le chaſim tobh, Sit tibi ſaluti;</hi> Be it to your Health, or your Health. But if they are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed and diſaffected towards any, as they are towards Chriſtians, then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Curſe, which Letters caba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtically reſolved, do amount to 165, and in one Word they imprecate 165 Curſes to him. <hi>Bnxtorf. Synag. Judaic. c.</hi> 28. <hi>de Nupt.</hi> What are they that curſe and damn in their Cups, Jews or Chriſtians? I wiſh they would, when they are ſober, think of theſe Things.</p>
               <p n="10">§. 10. Here's Evidence full enough for the Notion in which I take this Healthing; but whence doth it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe? who is the Inventor of it? Here's an Enquiry for a <hi>Polydore Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil,</hi> or ſome ſuch Man as he, or <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronymus Mercurialis.</hi> I muſt go no further than my own dim and ſhort Candle will help me. The Heathens might imitate the Jews, and uſe that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:53440:38"/>as a divine, which was a corrupted Sacrifice. So the Learned <hi>Gataker</hi> conceived, in his Annotations upon <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.18. The Peace-Offerings and Drink-Offerings of the Jews were by God's Appointment, and were <hi>Sacrificia ſalutaria, votiva, &amp; eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtica,</hi> called by the Seventy, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Dr. <hi>Outram de Sacrificiis, c.</hi> 11. and others. What the Devil bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows from God pure and uncorrupt, he leaveneth with his Malice, to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt God's People, and all that are deceived by him. God's People paid dear for what they borrowed from Heathen Idolaters, or took up in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of them.</p>
               <p>That Text in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.12, 13. is interpreted by ſundry learned Men to countenance what I am upon: <hi>But ye are they which forſake the Lord, and forget my holy Mountain; that prepare a Table for that Troop, and that fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh a Drink-Offering unto that Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> Here is their Sin; their Loſs and Miſery by it is ſet down by the Prophet. The Sin was forſaking the Lord, forgetting God's holy Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, not regarding his Worſhip in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> or Mount <hi>Sion;</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:53440:38"/>a Table for that Troop, and a Drink-Offering to that Number. In the Original, as you ſee in the Margin, the Troop is <hi>Gad,</hi> and the Number <hi>Meni.</hi> The Learned <hi>Dru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> giving to <hi>Jacobus Montanus</hi> his Opinion of <hi>Gen.</hi> 30.11. tells him, that ſome Interpreters do render <hi>Gad</hi> a <hi>Troop,</hi> and others <hi>Fortune. Gad,</hi> as the Hebrews witneſs, is Good Fortune, <hi>quam Graeci</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>vocant,</hi> and the Hebrews <hi>Muzzal Tobh. Caeterum Fortunae, quam</hi> Gad <hi>appellabant, veteres menſam inſtruebant.</hi> But the Ancients did prepare a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for Fortune, which they called <hi>Gad, Iſa.</hi> 56.11. <hi>Druſius de quaeſitis per Epiſtolam, Ep.</hi> 100. <hi>Grotius</hi> alſo obſerves, that <hi>Gad</hi> ſignifies Fortune, among the <hi>Hebrews, Chaldeans,</hi> and <hi>Arabians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Seventy tranſlate the Words, <hi>And have prepared a Table to Daemon, and fill'd a Mixture to Fortune.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meni</hi> is by <hi>Avenarius</hi> tranſlated <hi>Mercurius,</hi> an Idol worſhipped by the Merchants. So Mr. <hi>Pool, Engliſh Annotat.</hi> The Merchants ſacrificed to <hi>Maia</hi> and <hi>Mercurius,</hi> in the Month of <hi>May,</hi> praying for good Succeſs;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:53440:39"/>and theſe Deities and Idols were the Sun and Moon, under ſeveral Names, as <hi>Macrobius</hi> informs, <hi>Saturnal. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 12. So alſo <hi>Alexander ab Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro,</hi> lib. 3. <hi>Roſin. Antiq. Rom.</hi> lib. 2. cap. 9. <hi>&amp; Lilii Gyraldi Syntagma</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>The Hoſt of Heaven were in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber many, and ſacrificing to them, they ſacrificed to a Number; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, ſaith <hi>Sanctius,</hi> alluding to the Cuſtom of the Heathen, <hi>qui tot cya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thos libabant,</hi> who ſacrificed ſo many Cups, as there were Letters in his Name for whom they prayed. Hence let our Merchants, Perſons of great Ingenuity, Induſtry, and Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in the World, remember that they are Chriſtians, and to ſend out their Ships with Faith and Prayer, and wait for their return by Prayer ſtill, by Patience and Submiſſion to the Will of God; and give over drinking Healths for a good Voyage, a good Return and Succeſs, that they may not attribute their good or bad Succeſs to <hi>Mercury,</hi> or to a good and bad Fortune, but to the Goodneſs of God, and his trying Providences. Did but their Ships run as many Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards at Sea, as their Souls and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:53440:39"/>do by Land, by drinking, their Lives would be more careful than they be, and would, if ever, learn to pray by Land. I doubt not but there are as many good Men of them, as of any Profeſſion, that ſpill not their Wine upon the Ground in Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bations, as the Heathen did; nor make a Body, ſanctified to the Lord, as loathſom as a Swilling-Tub; but ſend forth their Stocks with the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of Prayer, and receive them with another of Thanksgiving. So there are too many that trade in Sin, and I beg their candid acceptance of this Digreſſion, upon occaſion of this particular Notice that is given of the Pagan Merchants Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition.</p>
               <p n="11">§. 11. The firſt coming in of this Healthing to the <hi>Britains,</hi> they have cauſe to remember with Sorrow; it was with wiſhing well, but doing ill, (at leaſt I cannot trace it higher.) The Story is to be found in <hi>Fabian</hi>'s Chronicle, and <hi>Hollingſhead,</hi> but I ſhall take it out of <hi>Rich. Verſtegan</hi>'s Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of decay'd Intelligence, <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 127. As this Lady <hi>Rowena</hi> was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beautiful, ſo was ſhe of a very
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:53440:40"/>comly Deportment, and <hi>Hengiſtas</hi> having invited King <hi>Vor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iger</hi> to a Supper at his new-built <hi>(Tong)</hi> Caſtle, cauſed that after Supper, ſhe came forth of her Chamber into the King's Preſence with a Cup of Gold filled with Wine in her Hand, making in a very ſeemly manner a low Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence unto the King, ſaid with a pleaſing Grace and Countenance, in our ancient Language. <hi>Waes Healt Hlaford Cynang,</hi> which being rightly expounded according to our preſent Speech: Be of Health Lord King. — <hi>Waes,</hi> now pronounced Wax, is as much as to ſay, <hi>Grow, Re,</hi> or <hi>Become;</hi> and <hi>Waes Heale,</hi> by corruption of Pronunciation, after wards became to be <hi>Waſſaile.</hi> The King not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding what ſhe ſaid, demanded it of his Chamber lain what it was; and when he knew, he asked him how he might anſwer her in her own Language, whereof being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, He ſaid unto her, <hi>Drink Heale;</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Drink Health.</hi> The King was ſo be-witched with this Lady, that he put away his own Chriſtian Queen, and married her, which was fatal to the <hi>Britains.</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:53440:40"/>King <hi>Vortiger</hi> might be as unacquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Complement, as he was with the <hi>Saxon</hi> Language; for the <hi>Britains</hi> uſed all freedom in their drinking, without any Compulſion or Obligation, as is remembred in that old Diſtick.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ecce Britannorum mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> eſt laudabilis iſte.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t bibat Arbitrio, Pocula quiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſuo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>Behold, the <hi>Britain</hi>'s way praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy is,</l>
                  <l>That every Man may drink what's Pleaſure is.</l>
               </q>
               <p>What Devourers of Ale the <hi>Saxons</hi> were, may be ſeen in <hi>Johannes Boe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi>'s Book, called, <hi>Mores, Leges, &amp; Ritus omnium Gentium,</hi> l. 3. c. 13. They would ſet a Pail before them full of Ale, and drink out of it in a Diſh, it is incredible how much they would drink, no Sow, nor Bull could ſwallow down ſo much. He that drank down the reſt, had a Garland of Flowers, or Roſes, given him as a Reward, and carried away the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And from them did proceed,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:53440:41"/>ſaith he, that damnable Cuſtom of drinking the ſtrongeſt Wines through all <hi>Germany,</hi> with unſpeakable Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief.— He is taken for an Enemy that will not pledg the Cups that are held out to him. So he. And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> records it,<note place="margin">The Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Proof.</note> 
                  <q>That the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who of all the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Nations, were leaſt given to drink, and commended for their Sobriety; learnt in the Low-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Wars to drown themſelves in exceſſive drinking, and by drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Health of others, to waſte their own. <bibl>
                        <hi>Annot. Eliz. Anno</hi> 1561. p. 318.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="12">§. 12. Becauſe I would not be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, but back what I have a good while ago laid up, as the Signification of Healthing, I will produce ſome ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry worthy Divines ſpeaking the ſame thing.</p>
               <p>Reverend Mr. <hi>Durham,</hi> in his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the ſeventh Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, gives his Judgment thus. <q>If we look narrowly into the thing it ſelf (altho Cuſtom, when it grows inveterate, weakeneth us in the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of things, yet) it will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:53440:41"/>be found to have riſen from Heatheniſh Idolaters, who uſed <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bamen Jovi, Baccho,</hi> &amp;c. And if it be ſuppoſed to help the Health of others, that cannot be expected from God, who hath given no ſuch Promiſe, it muſt therefore be from the Devil; it was called by the Heathen, <hi>Phiala Jovis,</hi> drinking of Health, being amongſt them, a piece of Drink-offering, or Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to their Idols, in the behalf of thoſe they mentioned in their drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or whoſe Healths they drank; and it is certain there is no <hi>Veſtigia</hi> of it in Chriſtianity, nor any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it; and Experience cleareth that many are grown ſuperſtitious in the uſe of it, as if the refuſing ſuch a thing were a Prejudice or Indignity to the Perſons mentioned; and that the Devil hath made uſe of it, as a Rower, to convey in much Drunkenneſs into the World. We think abſolutely ſafeſt to forbear it, and we are ſure there is no haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard. <bibl>So he, <hi>p.</hi> 391.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>See alſo the Saying of Reverend Mr. <hi>Sam. Ward,</hi> above quoted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:53440:42"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Arguments againſt Healthing, and Diſſuaſives from it, general and particular, as it implies Sacrifice and Prayer.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>§</hi> 1. I Do preſume, this Ceremony of Healthing had no better Inventer, than the firſt Deceiver, and Inventer of Sin, and his teachable and forward Diſciples joyning with him: He that order'd the Scene, made this Prologue to it, for them that are ſo apt to learn and act. And it is moſt likely to deceive, and take, becauſe it hath the face of Friendſhip, and the good looks of Love and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and he that diſſents from it, looks like ſome odd peeviſh Humo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, and unhewn piece of Moroſeneſs, that will not fall in, and cloſe in the ſquare of Society, and therefore is fitter to live by himſelf, and to keep home, than to come abroad. And if the Diſſent breed an Argument, the Conſenters clearly carry it by
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:53440:42"/>the Poll; and they that oppoſe it are judged to wrangle againſt Points of Honour, Civility, Breeding, good Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, good Nature, yea Innocency, and the received Guſtom of all Sorts and Qualities of well-tempered Men, Men of great Vertue and Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments. How ridiculous doth that odd Man look, that makes not one among them? as ridiculous as if he wore a high-crown'd Hat, lin'd and fac'd with Scruples, a deep Ruff, and a Fur-gown; as made up of Scruples, Formality and Seriouſneſs. This Ceremony is ſo innocent, that, what can be ſaid againſt it? I ſay, If no more but this, it would raiſe Preſumption into a rational Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that it is not good, becauſe ſo many, that I will not deſcribe, are ſo forward, ſo conſtant, ſo open at it, ſo urgent, and ſo quarrelſom about it; and becauſe others are ſo ready at a call, ſo apt to imitate, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited and apiſh at it: Whereas, if it were but ſo innocent and vertuous, as ſome paint it out to be, Men would be more averſe from it, not ſo publick in it, and ſoon grow weary of it.</p>
               <p>There are many Divine Rules
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:53440:43"/>given us by our heavenly Maſter, that are quite out of uſe in Society, and common Converſe; and we know that Men are ſlow to learn, and very baſhful openly to profeſs and ſhew what is truly good and pious. Healthing implies praying; if Men were called upon to pray without drinking, how mute would Healthers be? But now how forward to begin, how earneſt to exhort and preſs others to it? The reaſon of this is ſo plain, it need not be produced. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it ſhould be followed, becauſe vertuous Perſons ſometimes, and in ſome caſes uſe it, or laid aſide becauſe bad Men make an ill uſe of it, may deſerve a Reſolution, ſince it is none of the Vertues of vertuous Men, who do rather ſubmit in Complement, than commend, or approve of it.</p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. My buſineſs is to ſpeak of Healths: I have but little to ſay of the Imprecations and Execrations, ſo much in faſhion among evil Men. Their Healths, failly ſo called, are a Teſt, or a Drink-order, ſignificant of a. Faction, and rampant Inhuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. The very ſound of them ſtrikes Horror through the Ear into every
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:53440:43"/>Heart that is not caſed, or rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt with a Coat of Flint: I will not record them, but heartily wiſh their Conſciences (ſo much as is left) would recollect them, and ſpread them before their Faces, that they may be aſhamed, and repent of them, before the Pangs and Horrors of Death do apprehend them. Could <hi>Balaam</hi> turn his Tongue to theſe, if it had not been tied up and reſtrained from curſing <hi>Iſrael?</hi> How gracious had ſuch Men as theſe been with <hi>Barak?</hi> If theſe Champions had been baptized into <hi>Dagon</hi> and <hi>Aſhtaroth,</hi> it would have better become them to curſe in their Drink, as <hi>Goliah</hi> did <hi>David</hi> by his Gods. The Jews curſe Chriſtians, and the Pope doth curſe Hereticks. But what are they that drink, and curſe and damn their own Country-men, Fellow-Subjects, and Fellow-Souldiers, liſted under the ſame Banner, in the ſame Proteſtant Church? The Jews hold it lawful for them to be ſo drunk at the Feaſt of <hi>Purim,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Buxtorf, Synag. <hi>c. 24.</hi>
                  </note> till they cannot diſtinguiſh between bleſſed <hi>Mordecai</hi> and curſed <hi>Haman:</hi> The one they bleſs, the other they curſe, as the Enemy of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:53440:44"/>their Nation. But do our Damners never miſtake <hi>Haman</hi>'s and <hi>Morde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cai</hi>'s? curſe them who deſerve to be bleſſed? If this come in their ſight, I do earneſtly entreat them to look to that Laver in which they were baptized, and remember that they be ſure to renounce none but them, who were renounced in their Names; to read and believe their Creed, the coming of Chriſt to Judgment, the Reſurrection of the Dead, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life; to read and ſtudy, who are bleſſed in our Saviour's Sermon; to remember the firſt and great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, and the ſecond which is like to it. All theſe written upon their Hearts, will be a greater Glory to them, than all the Epitaphs upon the Tombs of their Anceſtors. And laſtly, If they would believe their own Senſes, that Men are mortal, and that they are Men, and then mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Correſpondency between their Lives and their Belief, their Morals and God's Commandments, their Practices and due Preparations for Death, that by doing thus, they may turn their Tongues to Prayer and Bleſſing. Of whom have they
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:53440:44"/>learnt to drink and curſe? If they think there is no better Life to come, why do they not make more, and better uſe of this? why do they not labour to lengthen this? If there be a Damnation in Hell to come, why do not they turn out of the common Road to it? If there be none, why are they ſo ſinful as to hate their Enemies? and how come they to be ſo moderate towards thoſe they hate, as to wiſh them no worſe than no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or that Evil which they do not believe? If you hate them with that mortal hatred, that you would drink and curſe them into Hell, as faſt as you pour down Cups, why will you, by drinking and curſing, throw your ſelves in after them, into the bottomleſs Pit? Do you think they will not be as hateful to you there as here, if you and they ſhould be ſo miſerable as to meet there? But by your Drink and Curſing, you cannot <hi>confound</hi> nor <hi>renounce,</hi> nor damn them thither, but you damn your ſelves meritoriouſly, and as ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually as you can. O turn! why will you dye?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:53440:45"/>But to be ſhort with you; there is no doubt, but all ſuch Healthing as imports, or is attended with marks of Faction, Hatred, Wrath, Bitterneſs, with Execration or Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, is as bad as Hatred was in <hi>Cain,</hi> or Murder, or any of thoſe Sins which are evil in themſelves, and damnable in their Merit. Yea more, you that have the Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon you to be Chriſtians, ſin in theſe things worſe than Heathens; yea, they are worſe in you, than in that Devil, who ſets up School to perfect Men in theſe Works of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. For you ſin againſt ſolemn Vows, againſt endearing Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, againſt Means and Methods of Grace, and many other Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Aggravation. Such kind of Healthing as this, is down-right Sin, and ſo much the greater, as it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in your Sport and Frolicks, and not always in your Exceſs and Madneſs. And your <hi>Huzza</hi>'s, Songs, Muſick, Drums and Trumpets, are to ſtill the Cries and Tremblings of Conſcience, and your Fleſh and Joynts, or to keep down your Hair from ſtanding on end with Horror;
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:53440:45"/>as the drumming about the Idol <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loch,</hi> did drown the Cries of poor In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants that fried in the brazen Arms of that Idol. If you ſpice your Healths with any gratings of Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Blaſphemy, Malice, Luxury, or any other Sin, they are materially and formally Sins, as any that are committed by the Sons of Men, and muſt be repented of, or elſe you would wiſh your ſelves out of Hell again, upon condition you might lick the Sores of a poor <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and fare as ill as he did at the rich Man's Doors. O therefore ceaſe to do evil, and learn to do well; and put away this Evil far from you, or cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly God will put you far from him! Whether you will or no, die you muſt, and perhaps by Drunken Clubs, one at anothers Heels, one this Week, and another the next, and ſo on, till all are gone, as ſome have done. There are ſome Sins, which are <hi>Peccata tacenda,</hi> and ſo there are <hi>Pocula tacenda,</hi> Healths not to be named, and they that drank were carried away as with a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, where they drunk no more.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:53440:46"/>§. 3. Having rid my Hands of thoſe groſſely depraved Cups; I will take in hand thoſe that have a fairer outſide: and with Reflection upon what hath been obſerved of the Cuſtoms of the Heathens, I frame my firſt Argument and Diſſuaſive from thence.</p>
               <p>Chriſtians ought not to drink, and converſe by drinking, after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Heathen. Their inſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing and entitling, or dedicating of their Cups was not a natural Action, for the Service of Nature; not a Dictate of natural Light and Reaſon, but idolatrous and ſuperſtitions, and a pleaſure to the Fleſh. Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they do, as purely natural and moral, may be done by us: but their Sacrificing, and Dedications of Cups were none of thoſe things. And even thoſe Actions which are as natural as eating and drinking, by Chriſtians muſt be regulated by the Word of God. Grace muſt be the Principle, God's Law the Rule, God's Glory the Intention, or the end of it, according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Whether you eat or drink, or whatever elſe you do, do
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:53440:46"/>all to the Glory of God.</hi> 1 Cor. 10.31. <hi>No Man liveth to himſelf, nor dieth to himſelf:</hi> Rom. 14.7. therefore no Man ſhould do any of the Actions of Life, to pleaſe himſlf, or to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as his End. Whether Health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, conſidered in its proper Notion, can be to the Glory of God, is put off till afterwards.</p>
               <p>That Chriſtians are to live ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly by their own peculiar Laws, is plain from the Apoſtles Doctrine, and not to do after the manner of the Heathen, under that very Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of their being Heathens. <hi>Walk not as other Gentiles walk, in the Vanity of their Mind:</hi> Epheſ. 4.17. <hi>Not in the Luſt of Concupiſcence, as the Gentiles that know not God:</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4.5. The Vanity of Mind, and Luſt of Concupiſcence are Sins in all Men, but the Exhortation is enforced from the Perſons, <hi>as the Gentils do,</hi> and one reaſon ſerves for all: <hi>We have not ſo learned Chriſt:</hi> Epheſ. 4.20. And becauſe of our Calling: 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.7. And theſe Reaſons bind us, that live remote from, and unmixed with Gentiles; and therefore cannot be a Scandal to them. And the Oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:53440:47"/>is carried on in other places: <hi>Ye cannot be partakers of the Table of the Lord, and Table of Devils; ye cannot drink the Cup of the Lord, and the Cup of Devils:</hi> which may be extended beyond a local Communication with them, to an imitation of them at the fartheſt diſtance from them: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.21. The famous Mr. <hi>Mead</hi> ſaith, <q>That <hi>Stephanus</hi> in his <hi>Theſaurus</hi> found ſome, who thought the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, in the Text did allude to that Cup <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, uſed among the Gentiles; and further ſaith, This was the Tenet of the Gentiles, that the Soveraign and Celeſtial Gods were to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped only <hi>purâ mente,</hi> and with Hymns and Praiſes, and that Sacriſices were only for <hi>Daemon;</hi> out of <hi>Porphyry, Triſmegiſt. Apuleus de Daemonio Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</hi> He therefore that had given him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Lord, the only Potentate, to the one and only Mediator Jeſus Chriſt, muſt have no Communion, no part in the Service of the many Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ators, Lords, or Daemon-Gods of the Nations.</q> So far that excellent Man, in his Apoſtacy of the latter times, <hi>c.</hi> 6. See alſo, if you pleaſe <hi>Conſtant.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:53440:47"/>Lexicon. Verb.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The Ancients, when the Tables were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved and taken away, did drink the Cup of the good <hi>Genius,</hi> like our Grace Cup, by which ſome under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <hi>Mercury,</hi> or <hi>Jupiter Soter,</hi> as was obſerved above. To us there is but one God, the giver of Health, and all other Mercies; and one Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator Jeſus Chriſt, through whom we ask and obtain. Now except we have ſome Intimation, that we may offer a Cup, a Health to God for any Perſon, through the Mediation of Chriſt, it is the ſafeſt way to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear. This way of arguing is not new, nor only an Apoſtolical Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſeneſs, but uſed by others. There is in the Works of St. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> a Tract <hi>de Rectitudine,</hi> of the Recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Catholick Converſation, where the Author runs over abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Heathen Practices, which Chriſtians muſt abſtain from, and this is one, <hi>Nullus in Convivio cogat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium plùs bibere quàm oportet:</hi> let no Man make another drink more than he ought (and Healthing is a kind of Conſtraint, as will appear by and by.) And St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> did adjure
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:53440:48"/>his Auditors by the dreadful Day of Judgment, that they abandon from their Feaſts, that filthy Cuſtom of drinking without meaſure, as the Poiſon of the <hi>Devil,</hi> and Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Pagans.</hi> Serm. <hi>de Temp.</hi> 232. <hi>&amp; eadem Dominica, S. Serm.</hi> 2. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to our ignorant, unreformed, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal Chriſtians, any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riviledg of Chriſtians, how will they fly upon you? what, am I a Pagan? what, am I a Heathen? And is there no force in an Argument drawn from our Diſtinction from Pagans, both in the Reaſon of the Learned, and common Senſe of the Vulgar, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Divinity of the Apoſtle? How frantick would a Feaſt of <hi>Anna Perenna,</hi> Healthing, and praying for many Years, be to a ſober Chriſtian? And what is healthing Health after Health in too common Meetings? Was it fooliſhly done of Heathens? and how wiſely is it done of us?</p>
               <p n="4">§. 4. Chriſtians ſhould eat and drink, and converſe as becometh Chriſtians, but ſuch are we, (it is our greateſt Glory and Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive): This Argument is an Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:53440:48"/>to the former. As we may with admiration and praiſe, ſay, as our Saviour ſaid upon another occaſion, <hi>We have Bread to eat, which the World knows not of:</hi> So we ought to uſe ſuch a way of eating and drinking toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, at our ordinary Tables, and common Viſits, as becomes thoſe that have a Table by our ſelves, always in the ſight of our Heavenly Father, and King of Kings. Our ordinary Meat and Drink do feed and refreſh thoſe Bodies that are joined to the Lord, and to riſe again in Glory: And therefore as we live for a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Service proper to Saints and Chriſtians, and die to riſe to a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative proper Glory; ſo certainly we ſhould eat and drink in ſuch a manner, not as thoſe Dogs do, that ſhall not eat of the Childrens Bread. And as we ſhould be careful to waſh the Heart from all defilement, that that which cometh out of us may not defile us, or others; ſo what we eat and drink ſhould be in a ſanctified manner, to a holy uſe. If this Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity be too ſtrict, all I will ſay is, the Glory of that Diſtinction which Grace makes between us and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:53440:49"/>and Infidels, is too great for us. Kings Children do not find fault with the reſtraint, that they may not live like Beggars or common People. St. <hi>Luke,</hi> in the holy Story of the Infancy of the Church, informs us, that the Believers did eat, (which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains their drinking alſo) <hi>with glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſingleneſs of Heart.</hi> Acts 2.48. And when in the rich City of <hi>Corinth,</hi> their Love-Feaſts were pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted to Drunkenneſs, the Apoſtle reproves, and reforms that prophane Abuſe of their Feaſts, and God vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited them with Sickneſſes and Death for it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. If any think they are tied too hard, ſeeing they enjoy Eſtates and Plenty, and are Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, except they may drink accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their quality and plenty; the <hi>Corinthians</hi> might plead the ſame, for ſome of them were wealthy. The more bountiful God is to us, the more careful ſhould we be not to offend him. We ſhould eat and drink as holily, as if we were to vindicate our ſelves from the Slanders of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, becauſe we are to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to God, and do eat in his ſight, when far enough from the cenſorious
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:53440:49"/>Eyes of Infidels. <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in his Apology relates the Chriſtian Cuſtom. <hi>Non priùs diſcumbitur, quàm oratio ad Deum praeguſtetur; editur quantum eſurientes capiunt, bibitur quantum pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicis eſt utile; ita ſaturantur, ut qui meminerint, etiam per noctem adoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Deum ſibi eſſe.</hi> They ſat not down before Prayer to God was firſt taſted; ſo much is eaten, as ſatisfied the hungry; ſo much is drunk, as is good for chaſt Perſons: They are ſo filled, as thoſe that remember they muſt worſhip God in the Night. <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus Gentes,</hi> c. 39. Such was their Feaſting. The Heathens defam'd their private Suppers, as infamous and profuſe; and the ſame <hi>Tertullian</hi> replies, as <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garenſes: Megarenſes obſonant, quaſi craſtinâ die morituri;</hi> that they did eat, as if they were to die next day. And <hi>Minutius Felix</hi> vindicates the Chriſtians from ſuch Aſperſions. <hi>Convivia non tantùm pudica colimus, ſed &amp; ſobria; nec enim indulgemus epulis, ut convivium mero ducimus, ſed gravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate hilaritatem temperamus.</hi> We do not lengthen our Feaſts with Wine, but temper our Mirth with gravity.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:53440:50"/>Theſe Primitive Fathers and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians took it for a Scandal and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour to be intemperate.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> gives us an account of their Way, and ſaith, <q>Let us exhort one another with a twofold Invitation out of the Law, Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God, and then thy Neighbour. — Let the ſecond be with an honeſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. — As before we eat, it is fit we praiſe the Lord, the Maker of all things; ſo when we drink, it becomes us to ſing unto him. <bibl>
                        <hi>Padag.</hi> I. 1. c. 4.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="5">§. 5. <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. The Occaſions of Sin, and innumerable evil Effects and Conſequences, are carefully and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcienciouſly to be avoided: but Healthing is the apparent and known Occaſion of many Sins and Miſeries. I muſt prove every Branch of this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, becauſe I bring my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Impeachments againſt this Uſage before Parties and Judges, that are corrupted, and bribed, and pre-ingaged.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:53440:50"/>1. That Occaſions of Sin have ſome kind of Cauſality, as the Object and Matter, is plain enough, but grant a difference between them: Yet as they are Occaſions, they are careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be ſhunn'd, or elſe we fall upon wilful Sins, by a wilful taking the occaſions of them. They that wait for Occaſions and Opportunities, do ſtay no longer out of the Snare, than the Snare is making for them, and lie in wait for their own deſtruction. But if Men have any fear of Death and Judgment, or any common a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion from Sin, they muſt not go in at the door of Occaſion, which the Devil and his Porters hold open to them. <hi>Solomon</hi> doth adviſe and charge us, that we ſhould not <hi>look upon the Wine when it is red, and giveth its colour in the Cup, when it mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth it ſelf aright:</hi> For the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour will inflame the Appetite, when it is look'd upon in earneſt; and then when the inflamed Appetite muſt be fed, Sin preys upon the enſnared Sinner; when it ſmiles in the Glaſs, it bites and ſtings like a Serpent in its Effects. <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.31, 32. It is not required that we muſt drink
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:53440:51"/>blindfold, we may ſee what we drink; but if the ſparkling of the Wine makes us dote upon it, and exceſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly covet it, then we are poyſoned by it, and it goes down ſmoothly, but bites like a Serpent, and ſtings like an Adder. The Miſchiefs of it are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſenſible and great, yea, deadly. The Wine that was red, was turn'd into an Adder or a Serpent; and a Man ſhould forbear fondly to look on the briskneſs of his Wine, as it is a Temptation, as he would refuſe to drink off that Cup that had a living Serpent in it. The wiſe Man doth dehort us from Occaſions and Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, becauſe of the deadly Effects thereof. If any deſpiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> in this, they deſpiſe both him that was the greateſt and wiſeſt of Kings, and the only wiſe God, who is infinitely greater than he, and he gives them warning. And what demonſtration can be ſo ſenſible, as what is taken from ſuch Effects? And they that feel not the point of the Argument, are in danger of Inſenſibleneſs and Stupidity, deſcribed in the laſt Verſe: <hi>They have ſtricken me, ſay they, and I was not ſick; they have beaten me, and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:53440:51"/>I felt it not.</hi> A deadly Diſeaſe doth ſeize upon the Conſcience; the Heart is untouched with the ſmartneſs of God's Judgments, until the Sting of Death take that faſt hold, that it can never be taken out. <hi>A prudent Man foreſeeth the Evil, and hideth himſelf; but the ſimple paſs on, and are puniſhed. Prov.</hi> 22.3. &amp; 27.12.</p>
               <p>I could be too tedious, to prove that Occaſions of Sin are to be eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewed, as the Doors and Entries into Sin. I will paſs from this to the Effects of Healthing, which are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding many; and becauſe the ill Effects are ſo many and notorious, they ſhould not be retain'd amongſt Men and Chriſtians. And if it be any Motive to us, as it ought to be, we have the Examples of Churches and Ages, who diſuſed and laid aſide an ancient, primitive, Chriſtian Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, becauſe it was an occaſion of much Diſſoluteneſs and Immorality. The <hi>Agapae,</hi> or Feaſts of Charity, which commenc'd with the firſt Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of Chriſtians at the Lord's-Table, and were continued for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Centuries in ſome Churches, were reproved, and put down, becauſe of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:53440:52"/>the Exorbitance of ungoverned Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and prohibited to be uſed in Churches, by ſeveral Canons of Councils. And after that thoſe Love-Feaſts were changed into Fealtings at the Memorials of Martyrs, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dications of Churches,<note place="margin">Ep. Ang. Aurel. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra citat. Serm. de Temp. <hi>232 S. 2,</hi> &amp;c.</note> they were met with there alſo, by the Zeal of holy Men, offended with the diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of thoſe Meetings, after the manner of Heathens. Their uſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, and reaſons why they were prohibited, may be ſeen in ſhort, but fully, in learned and laborious <hi>Horn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck, Vetera &amp; Nova,</hi> l. 1. c. 20. <hi>item Exam. Bullae de Feſtis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If ſuch a Cuſtom, well begun, and continued for good uſes, was repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and vacated, becauſe it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed and corrupted into Sin; ſhall we retain that which had no better an Inſtitution than you have ſeen, and is ſo pregnant of evil and terrible Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, which grow greater and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and worſe and worſe, almoſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day? They that retain it ſtill, in defiance of the many Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from Heaven againſt it, ſeem to be reſolved to continue in their Sins, whatever it ſhall coſt them or others.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:53440:52"/>I will not undertake to reckon the common Products of this fair-faced, inſinuating Cheat; it looks like Health, but it brings forth a Spawn of Deformities. 'Tis confeſſed, if this were not, as long as the Hearts of the Sons of Men are evil, theſe Streams of Iniquity will break out; but then this is a very plauſible occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for them, and gives colour and reputation to them, which without it, would nakedly appear uncomely Vices: <hi>Quid enim delectant damna ſine gratiâ?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt: Healthing is an Invitation, a Provocation, an Engagement to drink, not only as a Sign of Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and hearty Friendſhip, but an Obligation to drink, for drinking ſake. And according to the intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and affection of them that engage together, the Current of Evil that flows from it, is either higher or lower. If Men are prepared for a Debauch, for a Revenge, for a Victory, for Sport with the Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of ſome, then Healthing can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be waſh'd clean from their Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities: if it be in Pride, Oſtentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Generoſity, if to make a Party,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:53440:53"/>to pick a quarrel, to give offence, or to make an occaſion of quarrel, or diſcrimination of Affections and Parties, Healthing is as great a Sin as any of theſe are, and can be no more excuſed than any of the Works of Darkneſs. And as Healthings do multiply among us, as they do to a great exceſs; ſo the Peſtilence of contagious Manners breaks out, and a Man cannot come among them that have the Receipts and Arts of Poyſoning, but his Soul and Body are in danger of preſent Death. Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Sin is that Healthing is an Introduction to, and ſo made uſe of, Healthing is forbidden in that ſame Commandment in which that Sin is forbidden, that Men by Healthing fall into: for it is a known Rule in the Expoſition of the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that in what Commandment ſoever any Sin is forbidden, the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of that Sin are forbidden in that ſame Commandment. All the Sins that are drawn on by Healthing, run into it, and it is tainted with them, and therefore can never be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted from Pollution and Guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. It hath the ſame tendency to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:53440:53"/>Drunkenneſs, which is againſt many of God's Commandments, and other Sins, as the giving of a Lye, or a box of the Ear to a Quarrel, and that to drawing Blood and Murder: it hath the ſame tendency to the Sins that are drawn after it, that Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs and Dalliance hath to For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication and Adultery.</p>
               <p>Secondly; It is plain, by and in common Practice, a flattering Preface and Dedication before a whole Tome of Sins, and in particular, if not to down-right Drunkenneſs, yet to an Exceſs in Drinking. Thus indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Men take it, and ſo Parties find it. And this I prove by theſe Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is manifeſt, when Men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a Debauch, they begin with a Health, and proceed from ſome great one to give credit to the Work: and to deny a Health, is as much as to deny Duty or Honour to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron of that Cup, to whom the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication is made; ſo it was of old, and ſo it is ſtill. As St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates the manner of it. Then they drink to ſeveral Names or Perſons, not of the Living only, but of the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:53440:54"/>Dead, of Saints, of Angels, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they pay them Honour: <hi>Serm. de Temp. de Ebriet.</hi> §. 2. So <hi>Ambroſe</hi> above quoted. <hi>Apud Germanos Ebri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etatis contilianda gratia,</hi> ſaith <hi>Wen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delin. Lib. ſupra citate:</hi> When the <hi>Germans</hi> deſign a drunken Bout, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in Princes Courts, they have their <hi>Pocula Soteria,</hi> their Healthing Cups, which they drink to the Health of their Princes, and which they can by no means refuſe. So that ingenious <hi>Mercurius Britanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> ſaid to be the moſt Reverend Biſhop <hi>Hall,</hi> in his <hi>Mundus alter &amp; idem,</hi> deſcribes the Service of <hi>Bacchus, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3. One of the Gueſts having put off his Garland, with bended Knees, as if he were at Prayer, takes a Cup, holding a Pint and half, and ſaith, Here's a Health to <hi>Caguſtrius,</hi> the moſt Potent Arch-Duke of <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulia,</hi> (that is Drunken-Land): e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one from the higheſt to the loweſt, with the ſame Cup, Action, Geſture, approves himſelf a faithful Citizen, and well affected, or which he had rather, a ſtout Drinker. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther riſes up preſently after, and ſaith, <hi>Benè vos, benè nos,</hi> all Happineſs to
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:53440:54"/>you, and to us, and to the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and imperial City <hi>Zouffenberga.</hi> — A third drinks in Honour to <hi>Yurania,</hi> and the Nobles, and every one adds ſomething to allure the Company to new Draughts.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is an Engagement to drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if you conſider the Perſon that begins it, who, as he expects to be pledged, ſo they that follow, hold it Civility to follow their Leader.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If it ſtayeth, the ſtop or neglect is looked upon as a Default, and he that neglects, is called upon as to do his Duty; it muſt not die upon his Hands, or at his Door.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is often taken as an Affront, a Slight, a matter of wrangling, if not of Duelling and fouleſt Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It is looked upon as a Debt in the Bond of Civility and Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and paid as duly as a How-do-you: if one begins your Health, you muſt thank him, and call for his.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But what if it be an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement? what then? what harm is there in that?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:53440:55"/>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> No ſeeming harm at all to them that ſwallow Sins, and it never ſtays with them to make Conſcience ſick; but to them that walk and live nearer the Light of God's Law, it is apparently a Treſpaſs upon Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Goodneſs.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He that begins, makes himſelf a Debtor to pledg all that pledg him, as oft as any of them can hold out. He opens his Boſom to the Tempter, and all his Angels and Agents; they lay by their Armour, and take off their Watch againſt the Aſſaults of the Devil, or drinking Men to a wet Encounter, when they lay by their Hats out of Reverence to this Paganiſh Devotion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They who cannot bear much Drink, or are not forward to it, do by their Fear and Compliance give Countenance to the moſt ſhameleſs Soker, and harden him in his Sin, and are acceſſary to all his Exceſs, and juſtify his drinking many, by their drinking ſome.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By this means the worſt of Men have an opportunity to take in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, into a Partnerſhip in this
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:53440:55"/>trade of breaking, and going behind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand in all manner of Goodneſs: no Man ſhall carry away one Mite of Sobriety, but the beſt is become as bad as the worſt. A Man of a large Appetite, and profound Veſſel, that is an <hi>Infundibilum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Equites aurei dolii Mer. Brit. Aelian ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Hiſt.</note> a Tunnel, as one great Knight of the Golden Tun was called in <hi>Aelian.</hi> This Man who dies his Face to a Scarlet above a modeſt Bluſh, may be aſhamed to drink all, or moſt himſelf: Modeſty may make him take a turn in the Air, divert himſelf with ſome Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, or Exerciſe, and come to his Element by leiſure, even as Ducks that come ſometimes to Land. But when Healthing is up, he drinks but in a mode, hath a fair Pretence, even the Rule of the Company, for his pouring down, and all that can bear it are as bad as he. And where can you ſee a difference between one and another, while Healths are called and pledged, except that one can bear more than another.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is a Temptation to many weak Men, quickly to loſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by yielding.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:53440:56"/>5. It is a very plauſible Excuſe for loſs of Time, bad Hours, and an hundred Faults, for in Civility they could not break off, nor refuſe, it would be ill taken, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Let him look to it that begins; for tho all that pledg are guilty, yet they all lay the evil Conſquences up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him; as he that begins a Fray, is blam'd of all; they make his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning the great Fault, and their following too little to be repented of.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Many particular Perſons have been ſpoiled by it; and it hath been the beginning of many a Man's being given to Drink, and by that to his Ruine. Many Men were modeſt and ſober, and ſeem'd religious in their private Capacities, but being call'd to Office muſt be modiſh, and drink Healths, and according to their place begin them too. They have in time been throughly wet with a ſhower of Sin, gone home with Shame, and what then? either they muſt repent of it, and do ſo no more; and then they are <hi>Wh</hi>— or elſe they muſt turn it. into a leſt, and make little of it, and ſo become
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:53440:56"/>hardned in that, and other Sins. Healthing now is become one of the genteel Qualities of an Office.</p>
               <p n="8">8. It corrupts or divides Society. If a Man drink according to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and pleaſure of Companies, if he do not renounce and abjure Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of God, Modeſty, and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, he muſt put them off for a time. To refuſe Healths, looks as ill as a <hi>Truly</hi> founds meanly. We are miſerably disjoynted; and there is not any one thing that keeps us out of joynt more than factious and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory Healths. And if a Man be not of the ſame Party, he muſt drink, and groſly diſſemble his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affection, or hear of it. Holy, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, modeſt Perſons muſt keep home, for they are not qualified for publick Company.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The Evil of Healthing hath been ſo great a Sin and Provocation, that ſome have loſt their Lives by it, ſome have repented of it in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, as a great Sin; ſo did Mr. <hi>Francis Cartwright:</hi> See Mr. <hi>Bohon</hi>'s Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections. And one of the greateſt, and worthieſt of Honour, that ever this Nation bred, vow'd againſt it, and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:53440:57"/>kept his Vow, and that was the great Sir <hi>Matthew Hale:</hi> See his Life, <hi>p.</hi> 14. And tho he was afterwards preſt to drink Healths, (I wonder who had ſo little Reſpect or Reverence for him) particularly the King's, which was ſet up by too many, as a diſtinguiſhing mark of Loyalty, and drew many into great Exceſs after his Majeſties happy Reſtauration, but he would ne're diſpenſe with his Vow, tho he was ſometimes rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly treated for this, ſaith the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Dr. <hi>Burnet.</hi> And now let any Man of never ſo much Wit, ſhew as much for Healthing, as ever theſe two Inſtances againſt it, and he will ſay ſomething to bring up the Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on again to receive further Anſwers, when theſe are enervated.</p>
               <p>To conclude this Argument, I ſay confidently, that Healthing falls under the Imputation and Charge of all thoſe Faults, and fatal Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences that are occaſioned by it, and in probability had not been at thoſe times, but through it.</p>
               <p n="6">§. 6. But ſuppoſe it never had been attended with thoſe foul Effects
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:53440:57"/>of Drunkenneſs, or any other, take it ſimply in its own Nature, as it is a kind of <hi>Sacrifice</hi> or a <hi>Prayer,</hi> and let it appear as it is.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Take it as a Sacrifice to <hi>Health</hi> for any Perſon, and it is ſo putid, a heatheniſh, irrational Vanity, that I will not ſtand to expoſe it. <hi>Salus</hi> and <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> were helpleſs Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the blind and deluded Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then: they had a God for every thing, for every State of Man; one to be a Midwife, another to rock the Cradle, and ſo on, as St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> runs them over. <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 11. But to us there is but one God, as the wiſeſt of the Heathens alſo thought, that one <hi>Jupiter</hi> was in all thoſe Powers which the more ignorant adored. The ſimple and ruder ſort of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians carried their Banquets to the Sepulchers of the Martyrs, to be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by them; but did no Sacrifice to them. The Papiſts, like the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, built Altars and Temples to Saints, and had a Saint for every Artificer, for every Diſeaſe, <hi>&amp;c. Homily</hi> of the Peril of Idolatry, 2d Part. But while we have the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Men, and the Revelation from
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:53440:58"/>God, let us not come near in Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Heathens and Papiſts: Or, if it be a Sacrifice for Health, who is it offered to? the God that gives it? Where hath he required it? Or rather, is it not offered to the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack and Belly of him that drinks it? I loath to think of ſo vile a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, it looks ſo like an Imitation of them that ſacrificed among the Pagans.</p>
               <p>But the Notion I fix upon, is that which I think none can deny, that when we drink an Health, we ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify <hi>our good Wiſhes to the Party,</hi> and think this Interpretation of it, doth juſtify and excuſe it, and rather com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend than condemn it. But if this Notion will bear a Trial, I will try it, and ſearch into it.</p>
               <p>Let it be granted, that drinking to any Perſon is a Signification of Federacy, Love, Friendſhip, Peace, of Favour from a Superior to an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior, of Reſpect and Honour, if due Circumſtances be obſerved, from an Inferior to a Superior; and alſo we have ſeen Perſons of great Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to drink what they think beſt to another, with a deſire that he drink
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:53440:58"/>the ſame, becauſe it is thought to be the beſt, and by that the Stranger is encouraged to a Freedom, and that the beſt is for his Service. But when Healths are called for, and delivered, theſe things are quite altered, and I think perverted.</p>
               <p>To make out this Notion more diſtinctly:
<list>
                     <item>1. It is clear to us, that no Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is accepted with God, but what is according to his Will; and that he is the only Object of our Prayers, becauſe the Giver of all things.</item>
                     <item>2. Health, if it be taken largely, for all manner of outward good things, beneficial to Life and Health, or for ſpiritual Well-being, which comes within the Signification of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> or for that particular Bleſſing of bodily Health and Soundneſs; Health in all theſe Acceptations is an invaluable Mercy, and the loſs of it a very great Affliction and Miſery.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Hence I conclude two things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That no Man is fit to drink a Health, but he that at that time is
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:53440:59"/>fit to pray to the Holy God, the God of Heaven, by Jeſus Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>2. No Man is fit to pray, or to drink a Health, but he that is truly ſerious, and conſiders what he doth.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The reaſon of both is plain, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe drinking a Health, in the moſt innocent Notion of it, doth intimate, or is attended with a Prayer, or a good Wiſh to them they drink to; and that Prayer is, or ſhould be to the merciful God only, for one of the greateſt outward Mercies that Mankind can deſire or enjoy.</p>
               <p>If any Man ſay, This carries the Notion too high, for no Man deſigns to intereſt or concern God at all in a Health. (Truly it may be ſo, that it is furtheſt from the Heart of many.) But how can you drink a Health and not intereſt God in it? for if you wiſh well to the Perſon whoſe Health is drunk, and wiſh him ſo great a Mercy as Health is, in its loweſt Signification; you muſt wiſh it of God, for none can give or continue it but he; and if you do not ſeriouſly and heartily wiſh it of God, you do but delude, or mock, or hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritically complement your Friend,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:53440:59"/>whoſe Welfare you pretend ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to wiſh: you wiſh him Health, but do not intend therein to pray to God to give it. Here's now a Trial of the great Love of Healthers! But if you do heartily deſire that Mercy from God, how can you do it and not be ſerious? and make it a piece of your Devotion? It is ſeriouſly to be pray'd for, or not at all, for you ought not to diſſemble in the matter. If it be a ſerious good Wiſh or Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then, <hi>Procùl hinc, procùl ite profani, ſancta ſanctis.</hi> Healths are only to be drunk by holy and ſerious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: And I think they will hardly be brought to it upon the Premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and what's yet to follow.</p>
               <p>Firſt; Either you muſt joyn Drink and Prayer, or ſeparate them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If you joyn Drink and Prayer, whether mental or oral in a Health, then by whoſe Inſtitution do you drink and pray? by God's? or by Man's, by what Man, or what kind of Men? Doth Prayer ſanctify that Cup? or doth the Cup pollute the Prayer? or do you ſeem to pray for the Drink's ſake, and drink for your own pleaſure, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother's
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:53440:60"/>Health? I grant, and I wiſh it were more common, that we may pray and praiſe God as we drink: But then by what Authority of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution do I drink <hi>that Cup,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">☞</note> 
                  <hi>to that end that it may be to the Health of another Perſon?</hi> or what kind of ſign is it that I wiſh the Health of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when I drink? or what Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy hath any drinking upon anothes Conſtitution? If it had any Virtue at all to give, reſtore, or continue Health, either naturally, or by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. I would adviſe all Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians and Apothecaries to forbear it, becauſe it hinders them; and to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe againſt it, or to uſe it as the laſt Remedy, when they have had as many Fees as they deſire, before they try it: But they know it hath no virtue to that end, but rather the contrary, as ſometimes they find it to their Profit. What help doth their drinking afford to their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? What, is it like Water to a Mill? Drink turns about the Wheel of their Affections to make them more ardent in their Requeſts for Health? Or, is it becauſe they cannot wiſh well to others, but when they are
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:53440:60"/>pleaſing their own Senſe and Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite? or then their Devotions are as violent as Raptures, when they are tranſported, and in an Elevation? What a kind of carnal Fanaticiſm is this?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Or, though you do joyn Drink and Prayer, yet their Virtue is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and ſeparate; Prayer goes one way, and Drink another. Indeed I think they are better parted than joyn'd; and leſt God be diſhonoured by ſuch kind of Prayers, as the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality diſhonour him and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by ſuch kind of drinking; it were plain dealing for them to ſpeak the naked Truth, and ſay, when they drink, Here's to my ſelf: or, Here's to my own Health, and drink no more than will conſiſt with their Health, and promote it, and not hinder their holy and fervent Prayer for themſelves and others. Moderate drinking doth promote their own, but can never promote anothers, much leſs doth immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſave either, but endanger one at leaſt. When you pray, pray ſo that God may mercifully hear you; and when you drink, drink ſo that
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:53440:61"/>God may mercifully bleſs you. But away with theſe profane, uninſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, carnal Sacraments, leſt the Sin of Drinking cry louder than your Prayers. We have often ſeen how Drinking hath drowned Prayer, and carried away all ſenſe of God and Duty before it.</p>
               <p>What? whether God hear you, yea or no, you care not for that; drink you muſt, and drink you will! It is a Cuſtom and a Complement in faſhion, and if you keep Company, you muſt do as Company do, and you look no further. This is moſt like to be true. But if any be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to perſiſt in their way, I am alſo reſolved to proceed to argue againſt it, and dehort from it; and ſome Arguments are humbly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the moſt ſober and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and ſome earneſtly ſubmitted to the wiſe and diſcerning, and all to them that are highly guilty, to reclaim them if poſſible.</p>
               <p n="1">1. All Prayer for Health, and all other temporal Bleſſings, is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to God through our Mediator Chriſt, with Underſtanding, Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Mind, and Faith and Reverence,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:53440:61"/>in ſubordination to the hallowing of God's Name, and concurrence with doing his Will on Earth as it is in Heaven. But is drinking of Healths accompanied with ſuch a Prayer? I propoſe my Aſſumption by way of ſerious Queſtion, whence every con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering Man may conclude,</p>
               <p n="2">2. We ought to wiſh very well to our Neighbour, and to wiſh Health to them that want it, with Submiſſion to the Will of God, and a ſanctified Health to them that have it? And when ever we wiſh it, to be in a Diſpoſition of Mind to pray for it. But in drinking Healths, do we mind or regard theſe things? The Phyſician is ſerious in many Years hard ſtudy, in cautious Preſcription: The ſick and languiſhing are ſerious and patient in their Applications: And will not you be ſerious in wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it?</p>
               <p n="3">3. All Mercies that are wanting and deſirable are to be ſought for by proper means of divine Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Bleſſing. But ſeriouſly, Is drinking a Health, or Healths, a proper, a natural, a moral, an inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Means? a Means and Method
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:53440:62"/>that God ever bleſſed to ſo great an end? The Phyſician applies proper natural Means; the Chriſtian and the Divine uſes, and ſhould only uſe inſtituted Means to procure it; and is drinking Healths a proper, or a likely means to obtain it? Then Healthers, heal your ſelves of Gouts, Feavers, Surfeits.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When you drink a Health, do you mean that particular and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Mercy, or a Collection of Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Temporal Mercies? If the firſt; then why do you ſeek that above all? is it becauſe you place Felicity in it? know we not that Sickneſs brings us as near Felicity? or do you make Health your top-Mercy and your Idol? How many have you ever known attain Health that drunk it, (if you have, adviſe the ſick to drink Healths to themſelves in Sack and Claret, or Brandy, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſtrong and pleaſing Liquor.) If under Health, you comprehend ſpiritual Welfare and Salvation, (which you ought to wiſh continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for all you love and Honour) is drinking Healths a ſpiritual Means to procure it? If Healthing be a
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:53440:62"/>Means, why do you ſend for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to pray? and deſire your Friends to pray by you when you are ſick, and not for your Companions to drink by you? God is more diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by one days healthing, than he is honoured, or Salvation promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a <hi>Lent</hi> of Prayers, except they for ſake their Drinking. If a Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Devotion ſpring within them, it is made away like the Male Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> by the cruel Hands of Healthers; it is drown'd and ſmothered under this Cover.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Do not we plainly ſee there is a Repugnancy between theſe two? do not we ſee, that thorow-drinking doth caſt off all thorow-Prayer? or effectual thorow-Prayer doth pray away Healthing? Where there is a ſenſible Repugnance, can there be a true Conſiſtence, and Co-opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
               <p n="6">6. That which God diſlikes, ſhould not be followed; and do not we ſee how God diſlikes theſe Practices? How Men are given up to the ſtrong Deluſions of Wine and Strong-Drink? to the Mockage of Wine? ſee we not how Men are given up to
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:53440:63"/>fill up their meaſure of Iniquity, and cut ſhort their precious Lives? Do not we hear what Organs play at theſe Devotions? Do not we know and hear what Songs, inſtead of Pſalms? what Blaſphemy and Atheiſm, inſtead of God's Fear? what Curſing inſtead of Bleſſing? what Affronts are offered Heaven? and what Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence is offered to Hell? Are not Healthers commonly given up to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery and Senſuality? like Men forſaken of God, and poſſeſt of Satan? And how can any Men that have a Reverence, or Tenderneſs, or Zeal for God, give Countenance to Healthing, any more than to any other Sin, whether Whoredom or Murder? See in conſtant Obſervation at all Feaſts of Companies, Pariſh-Meetings, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections for Parliaments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who begin firſt, or hold out longeſt, and go through the whole Service, they that pray moſt, or ſwear moſt? that love their Neighbour, or hate him? Why will you joyn and imitate, or countenance ſuch Men in ſuch things? As you ſhould hate the Garments ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Fleſh, ſo you ſhould hate the Tables, Floors, Cups that are more
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:53440:63"/>than ſpotted with theſe Libations: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.8. <hi>For all Tables are full of vomiting and filthineſs, ſo that there is no place clean.</hi> If you thought ſo well of your earthly Tabernacles, as you do of your Halls, Houſes, Shops, you would no more ſet your Bodies on fire, than your Houſes: why will you partake in that Levity, Profaneneſs, Scorn, and Deriſion of true Seriouſneſs and Goodneſs in that ribbald, py-bald Wit and Folly, in the Factiouſneſs, and other Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients that make theſe Cups bitter to any Soul that hath any Senſe and Taſte? Theſe are ſome of the things that are mingled with your Prayers for Health, and Proſperity, and I know not what.</p>
               <p>And in my Mind, theſe things are highly aggravated, that they ſhould be the common uncontrolled Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in many publick Meetings, at a time, when very many are proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the utmoſt, for not receiving the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, and when many croud in, whether fit or unfit, and when ſo many Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers are by Law obliged to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament, as a Teſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:53440:64"/>Popery. What can come nearer the holy Inſtitution of our bleſſed Lord, than bleſſing of Cups, hallowing them with Prayers, hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and delivering them with Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers? (doth God take them ſo?) receiving them bare, and often ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kneeling or ſtanding up? And who is this Service done to? and what more unlike to the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than this? what more contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in Effects? and inconſiſtent with the Uſe and End of that divine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion! — But I muſt ſmother many other Conſiderations to make an end.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Which do you chieſly intend in Healthing, whether Praying, or Drinking? if Drinking, why will you prophane Prayer by a carnal Subordination of it to the Fleſh? if Prayer, why do you drink ſo much? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:53440:64"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Remedies and Antidotes againſt Healthing.</head>
               <p n="1">§. 1. ALL that hath been hitherto ſaid, might be made up in Antidotes againſt this Cup of moral Poiſon; to which I will more briefly add theſe following, which are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to none but them that will take them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As it was ſaid of old in another caſe, Go to <hi>Jordan;</hi> ſo ſay I, Go to the Font, to the Laver of Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and remember that you put on Chriſt, and were admitted into that Society, whereof he that was cruciſied, complained in his Extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>I thirſt,</hi> and is now exalted high above every Name, is Head, Maſter, Governour; and the Society are all Saints by Vow and Profeſſion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Value the Price and Purchaſe of Souls and Bodies; remember that both are not your own, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed by, and dedicated to the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:53440:65"/>Lord, you are bound to glorify him with both; you are not Debtors to the Fleſh, to live after the Fleſh; but if you would live, muſt mortify the Fleſh, and honour God in your Perſons, which you cannot do if you diſhonour even your Bodies, which are not for Drink any more than for Fornication, or Pride, or any other filthy Service.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider the Price of your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Mercies, of infinitely greater Worth than all the precious Jewels, the profuſe and prodigious <hi>Cajus</hi> diſſolved in Vinegar to drink them off. The Tenure by which you hold is the nobleſt by Gift, by the Covenant of Grace, for your uſe, but for his Glory; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31. If you do not like them upon theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, why do not you throw them up, and hold them ſo no longer? and then ſee the Conſequence!</p>
               <p n="4">4. By the Goſpel we are indulged a great Liberty in the Enjoyment of Creatures, we are under no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition and Reſtraint that was upon the Jews: But we are no where ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned Temperance and Sobriety, as by the Goſpel; none made ſuch Laws
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:53440:65"/>for the Appetite as Chriſt, who call'd them Bleſſed that are poor, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced a Wo to them that are full. He preferred <hi>Lazarus</hi> in his Sores, with Dogs, before the rich Man. <hi>Carnifices ſalutis, ventrem &amp; gulam, coercebat exemplis.</hi> Novatianus <hi>Epiſt. de Cibis Judaicis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Do not affect to be civil, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh, and genteel in thoſe things by which Sobriety, Modeſty, Seriouſneſs, and Holineſs are defaced. Grace, and pure Chriſtianity, are the moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble qualities, except we think the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature the meaneſt. And what's Gentility, but the World's old Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry newly trimm'd? an upſtart Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigner, that claims equal Privileges with Grace, if it doth not take the upper hand of it at moſt of our Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. If Men did affect to be rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate, and Chriſtians indeed, in all Converſation, and to be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed with gracious Habits, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Qualities and Graces, above all Qualities, no Book would be more ſtudied than the Bible, and what Chriſt teacheth would never be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But Men ſoon learn, becauſe they affect the Modes of
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:53440:66"/>Speech, and Actions, and Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, (and this of Healthing is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up as ſoon as any,) and carry it, as if it were a mean thing to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, and ſillineſs to be ſerious, and an odd thing to be ſtrict, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decent thing to be ſingular, where we ſhould not be ſingular indeed, that is, becauſe we ſhould all follow the Rules and Examples of our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in Heaven, the Teacher that came from God, to teach us the way to him.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Be not ſo much taken with the Modiſhneſs of this Complemental Snare, as not to be out of love, and in the utmoſt deteſtation of its ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Attendants. To this end frame and draw true Images of things, and take off the Vizors from the face of Healths; when it is enjoined as a Sign of Loyalty, (which I hope it will never be, that hath been forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by Royal Proclamation) then it will be ſoon enough. It was an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thegm of a moſt learned Stateſman, <hi>I will pray for the King's Health, and drink for my own.</hi> Sir <hi>Francis Bacon.</hi> When it can be proved to you, that it is a real Sign of Honour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:53440:66"/>or an Act of Civility, or Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity, Nobleneſs or Hoſpitality; and when it ends as well as it began, then take it up. But do not you find, that then Perſons drink together more like Friends, and leſs like Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, when there are no Healths drunk, than when there be? And do not you find it true, what St. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> obſerved, <hi>Rogas ad jucunditatem, cogis ad mortem; invitas ad prandium, efferre vis ad ſepulchrum, &amp;c.</hi> You invite to a Dinner, but they are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to their Grave, <hi>&amp;c. Vocatis ut amicos, emittitis ut inimicos:</hi> You in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite them as Friends, but ſend them out like Enemies.</p>
               <p>You may, if you will, ſee in Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, 1. Irreverence of God, taking his Name in vain. 2. No Kindneſs to your Friends, but their Health in pretence. 3. An ungrateful Abuſe of excellent Mercies, Wine and Strong-Beer, that loſe their comforting Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue by exceſs, and their Uſe by wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs. 4. Sin and Levity fac'd and painted with a deceiving Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Some drink in meer Bravery and Pride, or in Flattery, or out of Fear, or miſtaken Love, but moſt
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:53440:67"/>commonly from Self-love, and Senſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing.</p>
               <p>Secondly, draw right and lively <hi>Idea's</hi> and Images of that great Sin of Drunkenneſs, for deteſtation ſake. <hi>Laeſa eſt pietas, ubi irridetur ebrietas. Ambr.</hi> You may find enough to turn your Heart from it, if you will but ſearch for it. And is not this the daily Attendant upon Healthing? 'Tis the greateſt Diſgrace a Man can put upon himſelf or others. Why ſhall it not be reputed to be as great a diſhonour to be laid by the heels by this Sin, as to be put in the Stocks, or a Priſon? Suppoſe a Company of rude and impudent Servants ſhould combine to abuſe their Maſter, a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of noble Birth, and great Honour; to that end they ſhould wheedle and gull him into a pleaſant Humor, make him very merry; and when they have levell'd him down to a Familiarity, they take his place, and play the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; they then put out one Candle, and anon another, and then come the Grooms and Footmen, and paw upon him, and at laſt lay him under the Table, or in a meaner place. Thus the Divine Reaſon is abuſed
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:53440:67"/>by the Senſes, and the Inferiors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing little better, or rather in that worſe than Brutes, make ſport with their Maſter. Again, imagine a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Perſon to have many graceful and uſeful Servants under him, and if they be not true and officious to him, it is his Fault, and not theirs; and this noble Perſon being out of humor, he turns one out of his place, and then another, until he have left him none to help him: Would it not be a very ignoble Action? Would he not, when come to himſelf, repent, and do ſo no more? Is it not like this, when the noble Reaſon and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections are depraved by Luſt, do ſerve his Senſes, and the Members of his Body, even thoſe that were born with him, bred with him from the very Cradle, went to School with him, lay in the ſame Bed with him, and are as dear to him when he is himſelf, as his very Eyes, Hands, and Feet; but he doth caſt them off by the inſinuation of Wine; the Eyes fail, the Hands ſhake, the Legs wave like Reeds: <hi>Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pes, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> mens ſatis officium faciunt.</hi> And tho they are next day taken home again, yet
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:53440:68"/>for ought he knew, they were quite gone, never to be ſeen till the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. — It is a high Offence to our glorious Creator; it perverts the end of our Redemption; it unmans the Man, and is a contempt of Death, the Grave, and Hell it ſelf. If Men had any reverence for their God, Creator, Saviour, Sanctifier; if any honour to their own Nature; if any ſenſe of Mortality, and of the refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence this mortal Life hath to eternal Life, they would never live it thus, throw away their Time thus. How curious are Men of their own Pictures, of their Childrens Faces and Shapes, of the Monuments of their Anceſtors! how enraged at the violation of their Daughters! And will you with your own hands, by the ungrateful abuſe of Plenty, deprave, deſile, ſwill, and proſtitute your ſelves! What if you were ſtript by your own Servants, of your own Clothes, and they ſhould put on you their Liveries or Frocks? would you brook it? Yet a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is a Gentleman in the meaneſt Garb; but you are not Men, when you undreſs, or put off Sobriety. In a word, it is a great Sin, and what if
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:53440:68"/>the Lord find you ſo doing?</p>
               <p n="7">7. If you would not drink to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, nor health about, be ſure you do not begin. And know, there is an honour due to Temperance, as much as Chaſtity. If you would not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour the Chaſtity of the deareſt Friend, if you would take it for a diſhonour to have your Chaſtity at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, never tempt, or ſuffer Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance to be tempted; for Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Chaſtity are of the ſame great Family, tho but low in the World.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Prize and improve Retirement; ſtudy to bear it, and to be happy in it. And be no oftner, nor longer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, than good occaſion will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. And in your own Houſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God, be Maſter; ſuffer no Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to be drunk, nor any of them to play the Gentleman with Healths. And no Man of breeding or worth, will put you out of your own way.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Preſerve the purity of your Souls, as well as your Hands; the purity of your Bodies from Exceſs, as from all Uncleanneſs. And as you would not be a Companion of Thieves, neither in their Thievery, nor in their
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:53440:69"/>Priſons, nor in the place of Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, be not a Companion of Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards; for Thieves and they ſhall be condemned together. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9. And as ſleight of hand, and cunning conveyances of ſmall Things, are preparatory Exerciſes to the Art of Cheating; ſo is Healthing the initia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Ceremony in the Profeſſion and Society of Good-Fellows. Next to the purity of your own Perſons, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the purity of your own Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and then of Societies, which are corrupted commonly by nothing more, than by this wanton playing with plenty of the beſt of Creatures. Poor People, that labour hard, and drink Water or ſmall Beer, do not uſe it; nor you neither, but when you have the beſt, and wantonly waſte it.</p>
               <p n="10">10. If you have not experience of your own, you may ſoon be informed of the many Evils which befall others, and that this is the entrance into the Schools of Vanity and Iniquity, and the Chambers of Death. It is good for you to be eſtabliſhed with Grace, and not with Meats, ſaith the Apoſtle, and not with Drink, ſay I; and be
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:53440:69"/>reſolved neither to offend nor entice any, nor to impoſe upon any, nor to be impoſed upon, that you may not communicate your ſins to others, nor be partakers of other Mens ſins. Be ſober, and watch; and if Men will not contain themſelves, be as reſolute to refuſe, as others are to offer. Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity will do you more good, and bring you a greater Glory, than all theſe ſhews of Civility and Breeding, as this is thought to be, by them who firſt grow modiſh, then apiſh, and then bold, and then obdurate. And whether Healthing be a ſin, or ſinful, or how far it partakes or contracts, I humbly leave it to them that will pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſe this Diſcourſe; but this I think is too manifeſt, that it is an Inlet of a Flood of Sin in all parts of the Land, and doth more harm than Floods in Harveſt.</p>
               <p>I have but one thing more to do, to commend the Reader to the Grace of God, and Holineſs and Sobriety to his ſtudy, and conclude with thoſe grave Words of the great St. <hi>Auguſtin. Ergo Fratres chariſſimi, dum haec ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gero, me abſolvo apud Deum. Quicun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> me audire contempſerit, &amp; ad bibendum
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:53440:70"/>pronus fuerit, vel in convivio ſuo alios adjurare vel cogere voluerit, &amp; pro ſe, &amp; pro illis in die Judicii reus erit. Et quia, quod pejus eſt, aliqui etiam Clerici, qui hoc deberent prohibere, ipſi cogunt bibere aliquos plus quàm expedit, amodo incipiant &amp; ſeipſos corrigere, &amp; alios ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigare, ut cùm ante Tribunal Chriſti venerint, nec de ſuâ, nec de aliorum ebri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etate incurrant ſupplicium.</hi> Serm. de Temp. 232. &amp; in ead. Domin. Serm. 2.</p>
               <p>If All that has been ſaid by me, will not prevail on our common Healthers to leave off this ill Cuſtom, I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire them to read and ponder his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Proclamation (here adjoined) againſt vicious, debauch'd, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Perſons, and againſt drinking his Health, publiſhed a little after his Happy Reſtauration, in the Twelfth Year of his Reign.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="proclamation">
                           <head>CHARLES R.</head>
                           <p>SInce it hath pleaſed the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence, in ſo wonderful a manner, and by ways and means no leſs mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, than thoſe by which he did heretofore preſerve and reſtore his
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:53440:70"/>own choſen People, to reſtore Vs, and Our good Subjects to each other, and to ſhew Vs a very hopeful Proſpect, if not to put Vs already into poſſeſſion of that Peace, Happineſs and Security, with which this our Kingdom hath been heretofore bleſſed: It will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Vs all, in our ſeveral Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to acknowledg this tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent goodneſs of Almighty God in ſo ſeaſonable a conjuncture, with ſuch a Circumſpection, Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, and Reformation in Our Lives, that we may not drive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way that Mercy which ſo near ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proacheth Vs, by making Our ſelves (wholly) unworthy of it. And in Order hereunto, We think it high time to ſhew Our Diſlike of thoſe (againſt whom We have been ever enough offended, tho We could not in this manner de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it) who under pretence of Affection to Vs and our Service, aſſume to themſelves the liberty
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:53440:71"/>of Reviling, Threatning and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching others; and as much as in them lies, endeavour to ſtifle and divert their good Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to Our Service, and ſo to prevent that Reconciliation and Vnion of Hearts and Affections, which can only, with God's Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, make Vs rejoyce in each other, and keep Our Enemies from rejoycing.</p>
                           <p>There are likewiſe another ſort of Men, of whom we have heard much, &amp; are ſufficiently aſhamed, who ſpend their time in Taverns, Tipling-houſes, and Debauches, giving no other Evidence of their Affection to us, but in Drinking Our Health, and inveighing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all others, who are not of their own diſſolute temper: and who, in truth, have more diſcredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Our Cauſe, by the Licence of their Manners and Lives, than they could ever advance it by their Affection or Courage. We hope,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:53440:71"/>that this extraordinary way of delivering Vs all from all We feared, and almoſt bringing Vs to all We can reaſonably hope for, hath and will work upon the Hearts even of theſe Men, to that degree, that they will cordially renounce all that Licentiouſneſs, Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Impiety, with which they have been corrupted, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to corrupt others, and that they will hereafter become examples of Sobriety and Vertue, and make it appear, that what is paſt was rather the Vice of the Time, than of the Perſons, and the fitter to be forgotten together.</p>
                           <p>And, becauſe the fear of Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or apprehenſion of Our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, may have influence upon many, who will not be reſtrained by the Conſcience of their Duty, We do declare, That We will not exerciſe juſt Severity againſt any Malefactors, ſooner than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Men of diſſolute, debauch'd,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:53440:72"/>and profane Lives, with what parts ſoever they may be otherwiſe qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified and endowed; and We hope that all Perſons of Honour, or in Place and Authority, will ſo far aſſiſt Vs in diſcountenancing ſuch Men, that their Diſcretion and Shame will perſuade them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form what their Conſcience would not, and that the diſpleaſure of good Men towards them, may ſupply what the Laws have not, and, it may be, cannot well provide againſt, there being by the Licenſe and Coruption of the Times, and the depraved Nature of Men, many Enormities, Scandals, and Impieties, in Practice and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which Laws cannot well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, and conſequently not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough provide againſt, which may by the example and ſeverity of vertuous Men, be eaſily diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced, and by degrees ſuppreſſed.</p>
                           <p>However, for the more effectual reforming theſe Men, who are a
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:53440:72"/>diſcredit to the Nation, and unto any Cauſe they pretend to favour, and to wiſh well to: We require all Mayors, Sheriffs, and Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Peace, to be very vigilant and ſtrict in the diſcovery and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of all Diſſolute and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Perſons, and ſuch as blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the Name of God by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Swearing and Curſing, or revile or diſturb Miniſters, and deſpiſe the Publick Worſhip of God; that being firſt bound to the good Behaviour, they may be further proceeded againſt, and expoſed to ſhame, in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as the Laws of the Land, and the juſt and neceſſary Rules of Government ſhall direct or permit.</p>
                           <closer>God ſave the King.</closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:53440:73"/>I intended to produce ſome ſad Examples (of which there are too many) of the lamentable Effects of Healthing, but I ſhall only relate one, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At a Tavern near <hi>Cheapſide</hi> in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> certain Gentlemen drinking Healths to their Lords, on whom they had dependance, one deſperate Wretch ſteps to the Tables end, lays hold on a Pottle-pot full of Canary, ſwears a deep Oath, What will none here drink a Health to my noble Lord and Maſter? And ſo ſetting the Pottle-pot to his Mouth, drinks it off to the bottom, was not able to riſe up or to ſpeak when he had done, but fell into a deep ſnoring Sleep; and being removed, laid aſide, and covered by one of the Servants of the Houſe, attending the time of the drinking, was within the ſpace of two hours irrecoverably dead.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:53440:73"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
